<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Outdoorsy Indians - Camping Destinations</title>
<link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Our blog posts contain comprehensive information on popular camping desitnations.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.551</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Elk Neck State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/elk-neck-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://bloximages.newyork1.vip.townnews.com/bayjournal.com/content/tncms/assets/v3/editorial/0/17/0175c178-c200-11ea-8801-07ea43f906ea/5f0743eb2641d.image.jpg?resize=990%2C556" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Turkey point lighthouse</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Elk Neck State Park, nestled in North East, Maryland, offers an exceptional escape to nature. The park spans across a peninsula between Chesapeake Bay and the Elk River, making it a picturesque camping destination. Whether you’re planning a family trip or a solo adventure, Elk Neck provides a perfect blend of serenity and adventure. Here’s your guide to camping in this beautiful Maryland state park.</p>
<section id="campground-overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="campground-overview">Campground Overview</h2>
<p>Elk Neck State Park Campground is renowned for its well-maintained sites and stunning views. It features over 250 campsites suitable for tents, trailers, and RVs, each offering a unique way to enjoy the park’s natural beauty.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> Elk Neck State Park<br>
4395 Turkey Point Rd<br>
North East, MD 21901<br>
Contact: 410-287-5333</p>
<p>Camper Registration Office<br>
95 Campground Rd, North East, MD 21901</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/central/elkneck.aspx">Elk Neck State Park Official Website</a>.</p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d5445.500808594442!2d-75.98222436576154!3d39.48095845299916!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89c7bd0070271edf%3A0xa025444dd88d90cb!2sCamper%20Registration!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1715264346496!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<p>The campground offers several types of sites: - <strong>Basic sites:</strong> Ideal for tents, these sites include a fire ring and picnic table. - <strong>Electric sites:</strong> These provide electrical hookups, catering to RVs and trailers. - <strong>Full-service sites:</strong> Equipped with electricity, water, and sewer hookups, these sites offer the utmost convenience.</p>
<p>Amenities at the campground ensure a comfortable stay. These include: - Modern restrooms and hot showers - Dump stations for RVs - Camp store providing essentials and souvenirs - Playgrounds and picnic areas</p>
</section>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<p>Elk Neck State Park is a hub for outdoor activities. Here are some must-try adventures: - <strong>Hiking:</strong> Explore over 12 miles of trails. The trail to Turkey Point Lighthouse is a favorite, offering panoramic views of the Chesapeake Bay. - <strong>Boating and Fishing:</strong> Launch a boat from the park’s ramp or fish from the shore for bass, perch, and catfish. - <strong>Swimming:</strong> The park has a sandy beach on the Chesapeake Bay, perfect for swimming and sunbathing. - <strong>Wildlife Viewing:</strong> The park is a great spot for bird watching, with opportunities to see bald eagiles and ospreys.</p>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>The ideal time to visit Elk Neck State Park is from late spring to early fall. May through September offers warm weather, making it perfect for exploring trails and enjoying water activities. Fall brings stunning foliage, adding a colorful backdrop to your camping experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>Elk Neck State Park is a fantastic choice for families and pets. The campground offers several playgrounds, and the trails and beaches provide ample space for kids to explore. Pets are welcome in the park but must be kept on leashes. Some areas, like the beach, have restrictions, so it’s good to check the park’s pet policy when planning your visit.</p>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips">Safety Tips</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wildlife Caution:</strong> While wildlife encounters are a part of the park’s charm, always maintain a safe distance, especially from deer and foxes.</li>
<li><strong>Tick Prevention:</strong> The area is known for ticks. Use repellent and perform regular tick checks.</li>
<li><strong>Water Safety:</strong> Always supervise children near the water and wear life jackets when boating.</li>
<li><strong>Weather Awareness:</strong> Be prepared for sudden changes in weather by checking forecasts and having appropriate gear.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Camping at Elk Neck State Park offers an idyllic blend of adventure and tranquility. With its diverse campsites, ample amenities, and a plethora of activities, it promises a memorable outdoor experience. Remember to follow the safety tips and respect the natural habitat to ensure a safe and enjoyable visit. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/elk-neck-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://bloximages.newyork1.vip.townnews.com/bayjournal.com/content/tncms/assets/v3/editorial/0/17/0175c178-c200-11ea-8801-07ea43f906ea/5f0743eb2641d.image.jpg?resize=990%2C556" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Creek Lake State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/deep-creek-lake-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dynamic-media-cdn.tripadvisor.com/media/photo-o/09/31/6c/e8/deep-creek-lake-state.jpg?w=2000&amp;h=-1&amp;s=1" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Deep Creek Lake</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Deep Creek State Park, nestled in the heart of Maryland, offers a serene escape for nature lovers, adventurers, and families alike. This comprehensive guide will walk you through everything you need to know about camping at this beautiful destination.—</p>
<p>Deep Creek State Park spans over 1,800 acres and is located along the shores of Deep Creek Lake. The park is renowned for its breathtaking views, dense forests, and the shimmering waters of the lake. It’s a haven for both relaxation and recreation, making it a popular choice for campers throughout the year.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> 898 State Park Road, Swanton, MD 21561</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="http://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/western/deepcreek.aspx">Deep Creek State Park Official Website</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3078.1112755718555!2d-79.30071722403343!3d39.51197817159941!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89caab539d3ce1df%3A0xfe9f1aa9b991ad6f!2s898%20State%20Park%20Rd%2C%20Swanton%2C%20MD%2021561!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1695149121894!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Water Activities:</strong> With Deep Creek Lake at your doorstep, indulge in boating, fishing, swimming, and kayaking.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> The park boasts over 20 miles of hiking trails, ranging from easy to challenging.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Nature Center:</strong> Learn about the local flora and fauna at the park’s Discovery Center.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Winter Sports:</strong> During the colder months, enjoy snowshoeing, cross-country skiing, and ice fishing.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>While Deep Creek State Park is open year-round, the best time to visit depends on your interests:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Spring (April to June):</strong> Witness the park come alive with blooming flowers and greenery.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Summer (July to August):</strong> Ideal for water activities and enjoying the warm weather.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fall (September to November):</strong> Experience the mesmerizing fall foliage.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Winter (December to February):</strong> Perfect for snow sports and enjoying a winter wonderland.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>Deep Creek State Park is a family-friendly destination with playgrounds, picnic areas, and educational programs at the Discovery Center. Pets are welcome in specific areas of the park, including certain trails and day-use areas. However, it’s essential to keep them on a leash and clean up after them.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Standard Campsites:</strong> Basic sites suitable for tents and small RVs. They come with a fire ring and picnic table.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>RV Campsites:</strong> Larger sites equipped with electric hookups for RVs.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Mini Cabins:</strong> For those who prefer a bit more comfort, the park offers mini cabins with basic furnishings.</li>
</ol>
<section id="amenities" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="amenities">Amenities:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Restrooms with showers<br>
</li>
<li>Potable water stations<br>
</li>
<li>Dump stations for RVs<br>
</li>
<li>Boat launch ramps<br>
</li>
<li>Picnic areas<br>
</li>
<li>Firewood for sale</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> While it’s exciting to spot wildlife, remember to keep a safe distance and never feed the animals.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Campfires:</strong> Only light fires in designated fire rings and ensure they’re fully extinguished before leaving.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Water Safety:</strong> If participating in water activities, always wear a life jacket and be aware of the lake’s currents.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Trail Safety:</strong> Stick to marked trails, wear appropriate footwear, and inform someone of your hiking plans.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Weather:</strong> Maryland’s weather can be unpredictable. Always check the forecast before your trip and be prepared for sudden changes.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Deep Creek State Park offers an unparalleled camping experience with its diverse range of activities, scenic beauty, and well-maintained facilities. Whether you’re seeking adventure or relaxation, this park caters to all. Remember to respect the park’s rules and prioritize safety to ensure a memorable and enjoyable camping trip. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/deep-creek-lake-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://dynamic-media-cdn.tripadvisor.com/media/photo-o/09/31/6c/e8/deep-creek-lake-state.jpg?w=2000&amp;h=-1&amp;s=1" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cunningham Falls State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cunningham-falls-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://beentheredonethatwithkids.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/Cunningham-Falls-3-2048x1536.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Cunningham Falls Lake Beach</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Cunningham Falls State Park, nestled in the picturesque Catoctin Mountains of Maryland, is a haven for nature enthusiasts and families alike. With its breathtaking waterfalls, scenic hiking trails, and well-maintained campgrounds, it’s no wonder this park is a top destination for campers from all over the country.</p>
<p>Cunningham Falls State Park spans over 6,000 acres and is divided into two separate areas: the William Houck Area and the Manor Area. The William Houck Area is home to the park’s namesake, Cunningham Falls, as well as the lake and a portion of the camping facilities. The Manor Area, on the other hand, offers additional camping, the historic Catoctin Iron Furnace, and some picturesque hiking trails.</p>
<section id="address-and-website" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="address-and-website">Address and Website</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Address:</strong> 14039 Catoctin Hollow Road, Thurmont, MD 21788<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/western/cunningham.aspx">Cunningham Falls State Park Official Site</a></li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3073.191147168118!2d-77.46466312402808!3d39.62289977157821!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89c9c756d86bf04f%3A0x4a1fd19304826c3d!2s14039%20Catoctin%20Hollow%20Rd%2C%20Thurmont%2C%20MD%2021788!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1695149059888!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
</section>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> The park boasts a variety of hiking trails ranging from easy to challenging. The most popular trail leads to the 78-foot Cunningham Falls, the largest cascading waterfall in Maryland.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Swimming:</strong> During the summer months, the lake in the William Houck Area is a popular spot for swimming.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fishing:</strong> The park’s lake and streams are home to a variety of fish, making it a great spot for anglers.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Canoeing and Kayaking:</strong> The calm waters of the lake are perfect for a leisurely paddle.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Picnicking:</strong> There are several picnic areas throughout the park equipped with tables and grills.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Nature Programs:</strong> The park offers a range of nature programs and guided hikes for visitors of all ages.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>While Cunningham Falls State Park is open year-round, the best time to visit is during the spring and fall. Spring offers a burst of wildflowers and budding trees, while fall showcases a brilliant display of autumn foliage. Summer is also popular, especially for swimming, but it can get crowded.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>The park is very family-friendly with playgrounds, easy hiking trails, and swimming areas suitable for kids. Pets are allowed in certain areas of the park, but they must be kept on a leash at all times. It’s always a good idea to check the park’s website for any specific pet restrictions before your visit.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tent Sites:</strong> Basic sites with a fire ring and picnic table.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites:</strong> Equipped with electric hookups.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Cabins:</strong> Rustic cabins that can accommodate up to four people.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Amenities:</strong> Restrooms with showers, potable water stations, dump stations for RVs, and a camp store for basic supplies.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> While it’s exciting to spot wildlife, always maintain a safe distance. Never feed or approach animals.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Water Safety:</strong> If swimming, always keep an eye on children and avoid swimming alone.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> Stick to marked trails, wear appropriate footwear, and always let someone know where you’re going.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Campfires:</strong> Only light fires in designated fire rings or grills. Ensure the fire is completely out before leaving or going to bed.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Weather:</strong> The mountainous region can have sudden weather changes. Always check the forecast before your trip and be prepared for varying conditions.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Cunningham Falls State Park offers a perfect blend of natural beauty, recreational activities, and camping facilities. Whether you’re a seasoned camper or a first-timer, the park promises an unforgettable experience. Just remember to follow the safety guidelines and respect the park’s natural environment to ensure a safe and enjoyable trip for all.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cunningham-falls-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://beentheredonethatwithkids.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/Cunningham-Falls-3-2048x1536.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Big Run State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/big-run-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://deepcreeklakeproperty.sfo2.digitaloceanspaces.com/betsys-blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/05181127/big_run.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-1" title="Big Run State Park Photo Courtesy of Taylor-Made Deep Creek Vacations &amp; Sales"><img src="https://deepcreeklakeproperty.sfo2.digitaloceanspaces.com/betsys-blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/05181127/big_run.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="lake view wtih kayaks at the shore"></a></p>
<figcaption>Big Run State Park Photo Courtesy of Taylor-Made Deep Creek Vacations &amp; Sales</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Camping is an age-old tradition that allows us to connect with nature, unwind from the hustle and bustle of daily life, and create lasting memories with loved ones. One of the best places to experience the great outdoors in Maryland is Big Run State Park. Nestled in the heart of the state, this park offers a unique camping experience for both seasoned campers and first-timers.</p>
<p>Big Run State Park spans over 300 acres and is located at the southeastern base of Backbone Mountain. The park is surrounded by lush forests, serene lakes, and offers a picturesque view of the Savage River Reservoir. It’s a haven for nature lovers, offering a tranquil setting away from city life.</p>
<section id="address-and-website" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="address-and-website">Address and Website</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Address:</strong> 10368 Savage River Rd, Swanton, MD 21561, USA<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/western/BigRun/Camping.aspx">Maryland Department of Natural Resources - Big Run State Park</a></li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3076.670855560701!2d-79.14133022403186!3d39.54447857159314!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89caa699b10dad69%3A0xe30313f8268452b5!2s10368%20Savage%20River%20Rd%2C%20Swanton%2C%20MD%2021561!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1695148965080!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
</section>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> The park boasts several miles of hiking trails, ranging from easy to challenging. These trails offer breathtaking views of the surrounding landscapes.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing:</strong> The Savage River Reservoir is a popular spot for fishing. Anglers can expect to catch a variety of fish including bass, trout, and perch.</li>
<li><strong>Boating:</strong> Bring your kayak or canoe and paddle through the calm waters of the reservoir.</li>
<li><strong>Picnicking:</strong> There are several picnic areas equipped with tables and grills, perfect for a family outing.</li>
<li><strong>Wildlife Viewing:</strong> The park is home to diverse wildlife, including deer, birds, and small mammals.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>The ideal time to visit Big Run State Park is during the spring and fall months. During these times, the weather is mild, the foliage is vibrant, and the park is less crowded. Summer is also a popular time, especially for water activities, but expect larger crowds.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>Big Run State Park is a family-friendly destination. There are playgrounds for kids and open spaces for them to run around and play. Pets are also welcome in the park, but they must be kept on a leash at all times. There are designated pet-friendly areas and trails where you can take your furry friend for a walk.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tent Sites:</strong> Basic sites with a flat area for tents, a fire ring, and a picnic table.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites:</strong> These sites come with electric hookups and are spacious enough to accommodate large RVs.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Cabins:</strong> For those who prefer a bit more comfort, the park offers cabins equipped with basic amenities.</li>
</ul>
<section id="amenities" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="amenities">Amenities:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Restrooms with showers<br>
</li>
<li>Potable water stations<br>
</li>
<li>Dump station for RVs<br>
</li>
<li>Firewood for sale<br>
</li>
<li>Boat launch area</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips">Safety Tips</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> While it’s exciting to spot wildlife, always maintain a safe distance. Never feed or approach wild animals.</li>
<li><strong>Fire Safety:</strong> Always put out campfires completely before leaving the site or going to bed.</li>
<li><strong>Stay on Marked Trails:</strong> When hiking, stick to the marked trails to avoid getting lost.</li>
<li><strong>Weather:</strong> Check the weather forecast before your trip. Be prepared for sudden changes, especially if you’re planning to be on the water.</li>
<li><strong>Emergency Numbers:</strong> Keep a list of emergency numbers, including the park office, handy.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Big Run State Park is a gem in Maryland’s crown of natural wonders. Whether you’re looking for a weekend getaway or an extended stay, this park offers something for everyone. Remember to respect nature, follow the safety guidelines, and most importantly, enjoy the beauty and tranquility that Big Run State Park has to offer. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>



</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/big-run-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://deepcreeklakeproperty.sfo2.digitaloceanspaces.com/betsys-blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/05181127/big_run.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Assateague State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/assateague-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/camping/wild-horses-assateague-island.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’re yearning for a camping experience that combines the enchanting serenity of the ocean with the raw beauty of nature, Assateague State Park in Maryland is the destination you’ve been dreaming of. Situated along the pristine shores and wild landscapes of Assateague Island, this park is a haven for campers looking for an unforgettable coastal getaway.</p>
<p>Assateague State Park is Maryland’s only oceanfront park, stretching over two miles of picturesque beachfront. But what truly sets this park apart is its famous wild residents: the Assateague wild horses. These beautiful creatures can often be spotted wandering the shores and marshes, presenting a unique spectacle for visitors.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> 7307 Stephen Decatur Hwy, Berlin, MD 21811, USA</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/eastern/assateague.aspx">Assateague State Park’s official site</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3133.1576105346007!2d-75.16397612484178!3d38.25265047186887!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89b92583f66fb6b5%3A0x72adfe8928d04344!2s7307%20Stephen%20Decatur%20Hwy%2C%20Berlin%2C%20MD%2021811!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694388214140!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Beach Activities</strong> : From sunbathing and swimming to surfing and beachcombing, Assateague’s pristine beaches offer countless ways to relax and enjoy the ocean.</li>
<li><strong>Hiking</strong> : There are several nature trails available, guiding visitors through dunes, forests, and marshes, showcasing the park’s diverse ecosystems.</li>
<li><strong>Wild Horse Viewing</strong> : Remember to admire these wild beauties from a distance to ensure their safety and yours.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing</strong> : Try your hand at surf fishing or bay-side fishing. A fishing license might be required.</li>
<li><strong>Bird Watching</strong> : The island’s rich biodiversity attracts a variety of bird species, making it a hotspot for bird enthusiasts.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-year-to-visit">Best Time of Year to Visit</h2>
<p>The most popular times to visit Assateague State Park are late spring to early fall, with the peak being the summer months. The weather is pleasant, and all the park’s amenities are in full swing. However, if you prefer a quieter experience, consider visiting during the shoulder seasons (late spring or early fall).</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>The park is undoubtedly family-friendly, with activities that children of all ages can enjoy, like beach fun, nature trails, and horse sightings.</p>
<p>As for pets, while they are welcomed in the park’s day-use areas, they are <em>not</em> allowed in the camping areas, for the safety and comfort of all visitors and the wild horses.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<p>The park offers a range of campsites to cater to various preferences:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tent Sites</strong>: Basic sites with space for tents and campfires.</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites</strong>: These sites accommodate larger vehicles and offer electrical hookups.</li>
<li><strong>Group Camping</strong>: Special areas dedicated to larger groups.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Restrooms with hot showers</li>
<li>Picnic tables and fire rings at each campsite</li>
<li>Camp store with essential supplies</li>
<li>Playground for children</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wild Horses</strong> : Always maintain a safe distance. Never feed or attempt to touch them.</li>
<li><strong>Weather</strong> : Coastal weather can change rapidly. Always be prepared for unexpected rain or wind.</li>
<li><strong>Tides</strong> : If you’re by the beach or engaging in fishing, be mindful of the tide schedules.</li>
<li><strong>Insects</strong> : Mosquitoes and flies can be quite active, especially in the warmer months. Bring insect repellent and prepare accordingly.</li>
<li><strong>Campfires</strong> : Only light fires in designated areas, and always extinguish them thoroughly before leaving or sleeping.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, camping at Assateague State Park offers an experience that’s hard to match elsewhere. The combination of unspoiled beaches, wild horses, and natural beauty create an atmosphere that promises memories for a lifetime. As with any outdoor activity, always prioritize safety and respect for the environment and its inhabitants. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/assateague-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/camping/wild-horses-assateague-island.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cedarville State Forest Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cedarville-state-forest/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.roverpass.com/system/pictures/images/000/035/900/full/ML16.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Cedarville State Forest Pond</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Situated in the heart of the Old Line State, Cedarville State Forest offers visitors a chance to reconnect with nature, find tranquility, and embark on exciting outdoor adventures. This 3,510-acre woodland reserve is the epitome of Maryland’s beautiful landscape.</p>
<p>Cedarville State Forest Campground is a reflection of Maryland’s natural beauty with dense woodlands, fragrant flora, and teeming wildlife. Tucked away from the hustle and bustle of city life, this sanctuary provides a serene backdrop for families, solo adventurers, and couples.</p>
<p><strong>Address</strong> : 10201 Bee Oak Road, Brandywine, MD 20613</p>
<p><strong>Website</strong> : <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/southern/Cedarville/Camping.aspx">Cedarville State Forest - Department of Natural Resources</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3116.0952749229946!2d-76.83255022481893!3d38.646689571778566!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89b7a1fcc93bb1a7%3A0x8f898a45e70db8ea!2s10201%20Bee%20Oak%20Rd%2C%20Brandywine%2C%20MD%2020613!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694387226273!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking</strong> : With over 19 miles of marked trails, Cedarville State Forest is a haven for hikers of all skill levels. The trails offer scenic views of native plants and wildlife.</li>
<li><strong>Picnicking</strong> : There are designated areas with tables where you can enjoy a meal surrounded by nature.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing</strong> : Bring your fishing pole and try your luck in the ponds stocked with bluegill, bass, and catfish.</li>
<li><strong>Nature and Wildlife Watching</strong> : Be on the lookout for deer, turkey, fox, and a variety of bird species.</li>
<li><strong>Horseback Riding</strong> : Certain trails are designated for equestrian use. Just remember to bring your own horse!</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>Spring (late April to early June) and fall (September to October) are ideal for visiting Cedarville State Forest. The temperatures are mild, the forest is teeming with life, and the colors of the changing foliage (especially in the fall) make for a picturesque environment.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>Cedarville is perfect for families. Children can learn about nature, enjoy open spaces, and participate in ranger-led programs (available seasonally). The campground is also pet-friendly, but remember to keep dogs on a leash at all times and clean up after them.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tent Sites</strong> : These basic sites are equipped with a picnic table and fire ring.</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites</strong> : While there are no hookups, there are designated spots for RVs with level grounds.</li>
<li><strong>Group Camping Areas</strong> : These are perfect for larger gatherings or events.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities</strong>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Restrooms and shower facilities</li>
<li>Potable water sources</li>
<li>Picnic areas with tables and grills</li>
<li>Playground for children</li>
<li>Dump station for RVs</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife</strong> : Remember, you are in their home. Always observe from a distance, do not feed them, and secure your food.</li>
<li><strong>Ticks and Bugs</strong> : Wear insect repellent and check for ticks after hiking or spending time in wooded areas.</li>
<li><strong>Fire Safety</strong> : Only start fires in designated areas or rings. Always put out fires completely before leaving or sleeping.</li>
<li><strong>Stay on Marked Trails</strong> : It’s easy to get lost in the forest. Stay on marked trails and always let someone know where you’re going.</li>
<li><strong>Weather</strong> : Be prepared for sudden weather changes, especially if you’re camping in transitional seasons.</li>
<li><strong>Water Safety</strong> : If you’re fishing or near water bodies, always supervise children and be cautious of slippery banks.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Cedarville State Forest in Maryland is a delightful destination for anyone looking to immerse themselves in nature. Whether you’re a seasoned camper or a first-timer, the forest’s beauty and serenity will surely captivate you. Remember to always follow the safety guidelines to ensure a memorable and enjoyable experience. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only.For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly.Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cedarville-state-forest/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.roverpass.com/system/pictures/images/000/035/900/full/ML16.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rocky Gap State Park Campground, MD, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/rocky-gap-state-park/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://marylandroadtrips.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/MRT-Lake-Habeeb.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://marylandroadtrips.com/design-your-perfect-escape-at-rocky-gap-state-park/">Photo Credit: Colleen Mulvihill </a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Rocky Gap State Park, nestled in the heart of Maryland, is a premier destination for nature enthusiasts, families, and campers alike. Whether you’re an experienced camper or a beginner looking for a refreshing escape, this picturesque state park offers a myriad of activities and experiences to create lasting memories.</p>
<p>Located on over 3,000 acres, Rocky Gap State Park is an epitome of tranquility, with the 243-acre Lake Habeeb at its heart. The captivating “blue waters” of the lake, contrasted against the thickly forested mountainside, are a sight to behold and offer a serene backdrop for an adventurous camping trip.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> 17600 Campers Hill Drive, Flintstone MD 21530, Ph. No.&nbsp;443-603-6324</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/pages/western/rockygap.aspx">Official Maryland Department of Natural Resources Page for Rocky Gap State Park</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3068.9799691271523!2d-78.64467522402346!3d39.71763287156056!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89ca60310295cc77%3A0x58d0a77aab302d3!2s17600%20Campers%20Hill%20Dr%2C%20Flintstone%2C%20MD%2021530!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694386775827!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade"></iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> With over 15 miles of trails, hikers can choose from a variety of difficulty levels. The ‘Canyon Overlook Trail’ offers a breathtaking view of the gorge.</li>
<li><strong>Water Activities:</strong> Lake Habeeb offers swimming beaches, fishing opportunities (trout, catfish, and panfish, to name a few), and boating. Rent a canoe, kayak, or paddleboat and explore the lake’s beauty.</li>
<li><strong>Nature Programs:</strong> Engage in interpretative programs offered by park naturalists, from guided hikes to talks about local wildlife.</li>
<li><strong>Bird Watching:</strong> For avian enthusiasts, the park is home to numerous bird species, including the rare bald eagle.</li>
<li><strong>Hunting:</strong> During hunting seasons, designated parts of the park are open to hunting.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>While Rocky Gap is open year-round, the <strong>spring and fall</strong> are particularly spectacular. Spring blossoms and fall foliage make for captivating vistas. However, summer remains popular for water activities and camping, with temperatures conducive for outdoor fun.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p><strong>Family-friendly:</strong> Absolutely! Rocky Gap is perfect for families, with a range of activities suitable for all ages – from playgrounds for the little ones to fishing for the grown-ups.</p>
<p><strong>Pet-friendly:</strong> Yes, pets are allowed in certain camping loops. Always remember to keep your pets on a leash and clean up after them to maintain the park’s pristine condition.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Standard Campsites:</strong> Ideal for tents and smaller RVs.</li>
<li><strong>Electric Hookup Campsites:</strong> Perfect for RV campers.</li>
<li><strong>Mini Cabins:</strong> For those who prefer a more structured setting without the hassle of pitching a tent.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Bathhouses with hot showers and flush toilets</li>
<li>Camp store for essentials and firewood</li>
<li>Picnic tables and fire rings at each site</li>
<li>Playground facilities</li>
<li>Dump station for RVs</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips">Safety Tips:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> While the park is home to various wildlife, it’s essential to maintain a distance. Do not feed or approach animals.</li>
<li><strong>Ticks and Mosquitoes:</strong> Use insect repellent and check for ticks daily, especially after hiking.</li>
<li><strong>Campfires:</strong> Only start fires in designated rings or grills. Ensure the fire is completely out before leaving.</li>
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> Stay on designated trails, wear appropriate footwear, and always inform someone if you’re going on a long hike.</li>
<li><strong>Swimming:</strong> Only swim in designated areas and always supervise children.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Rocky Gap State Park offers a unique blend of serenity, adventure, and natural beauty. Whether you’re looking for a peaceful retreat or a series of adventures, this is the place to be. Always remember to respect nature, keep safety a priority, and leave no trace to ensure that the park remains a sanctuary for generations to come.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>(USA) Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/rocky-gap-state-park/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://marylandroadtrips.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/MRT-Lake-Habeeb.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
