<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Outdoorsy Indians</title>
<link>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Our blog posts contain comprehensive information on popular camping desitnations.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.433</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Assateague State Park Campground, Maryland, USA</title>
  <link>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/assateague-state-park.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/https:/images.unsplash.com/photo-1627414878948-9c76dc53b342?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8fA%3D%3D&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=2940&amp;q=80" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@saralea?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Sara Cottle</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/REQqhtK5zkI?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’re yearning for a camping experience that combines the enchanting serenity of the ocean with the raw beauty of nature, Assateague State Park in Maryland is the destination you’ve been dreaming of. Situated along the pristine shores and wild landscapes of Assateague Island, this park is a haven for campers looking for an unforgettable coastal getaway.</p>
<p>Assateague State Park is Maryland’s only oceanfront park, stretching over two miles of picturesque beachfront. But what truly sets this park apart is its famous wild residents: the Assateague wild horses. These beautiful creatures can often be spotted wandering the shores and marshes, presenting a unique spectacle for visitors.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> 7307 Stephen Decatur Hwy, Berlin, MD 21811, USA</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/eastern/assateague.aspx">Assateague State Park’s official site</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3133.1576105346007!2d-75.16397612484178!3d38.25265047186887!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89b92583f66fb6b5%3A0x72adfe8928d04344!2s7307%20Stephen%20Decatur%20Hwy%2C%20Berlin%2C%20MD%2021811!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694388214140!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade">
</iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Beach Activities</strong> : From sunbathing and swimming to surfing and beachcombing, Assateague’s pristine beaches offer countless ways to relax and enjoy the ocean.</li>
<li><strong>Hiking</strong> : There are several nature trails available, guiding visitors through dunes, forests, and marshes, showcasing the park’s diverse ecosystems.</li>
<li><strong>Wild Horse Viewing</strong> : Remember to admire these wild beauties from a distance to ensure their safety and yours.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing</strong> : Try your hand at surf fishing or bay-side fishing. A fishing license might be required.</li>
<li><strong>Bird Watching</strong> : The island’s rich biodiversity attracts a variety of bird species, making it a hotspot for bird enthusiasts.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-year-to-visit">Best Time of Year to Visit</h2>
<p>The most popular times to visit Assateague State Park are late spring to early fall, with the peak being the summer months. The weather is pleasant, and all the park’s amenities are in full swing. However, if you prefer a quieter experience, consider visiting during the shoulder seasons (late spring or early fall).</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>The park is undoubtedly family-friendly, with activities that children of all ages can enjoy, like beach fun, nature trails, and horse sightings.</p>
<p>As for pets, while they are welcomed in the park’s day-use areas, they are <em>not</em> allowed in the camping areas, for the safety and comfort of all visitors and the wild horses.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<p>The park offers a range of campsites to cater to various preferences:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tent Sites</strong>: Basic sites with space for tents and campfires.</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites</strong>: These sites accommodate larger vehicles and offer electrical hookups.</li>
<li><strong>Group Camping</strong>: Special areas dedicated to larger groups.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Restrooms with hot showers</li>
<li>Picnic tables and fire rings at each campsite</li>
<li>Camp store with essential supplies</li>
<li>Playground for children</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wild Horses</strong> : Always maintain a safe distance. Never feed or attempt to touch them.</li>
<li><strong>Weather</strong> : Coastal weather can change rapidly. Always be prepared for unexpected rain or wind.</li>
<li><strong>Tides</strong> : If you’re by the beach or engaging in fishing, be mindful of the tide schedules.</li>
<li><strong>Insects</strong> : Mosquitoes and flies can be quite active, especially in the warmer months. Bring insect repellent and prepare accordingly.</li>
<li><strong>Campfires</strong> : Only light fires in designated areas, and always extinguish them thoroughly before leaving or sleeping.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, camping at Assateague State Park offers an experience that’s hard to match elsewhere. The combination of unspoiled beaches, wild horses, and natural beauty create an atmosphere that promises memories for a lifetime. As with any outdoor activity, always prioritize safety and respect for the environment and its inhabitants. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>USA, Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/assateague-state-park.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cedarville State Forest Campground, Maryland, USA</title>
  <link>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cedarville-state-forest.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/https:/dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/PublishingImages/Cedarville_SpringReflections_TerryThomas.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Cedarville State Forest Pond</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Situated in the heart of the Old Line State, Cedarville State Forest offers visitors a chance to reconnect with nature, find tranquility, and embark on exciting outdoor adventures. This 3,510-acre woodland reserve is the epitome of Maryland’s beautiful landscape.</p>
<p>Cedarville State Forest Campground is a reflection of Maryland’s natural beauty with dense woodlands, fragrant flora, and teeming wildlife. Tucked away from the hustle and bustle of city life, this sanctuary provides a serene backdrop for families, solo adventurers, and couples.</p>
<p><strong>Address</strong> : 10201 Bee Oak Road, Brandywine, MD 20613</p>
<p><strong>Website</strong> : <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/Pages/southern/Cedarville/Camping.aspx">Cedarville State Forest - Department of Natural Resources</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3116.0952749229946!2d-76.83255022481893!3d38.646689571778566!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89b7a1fcc93bb1a7%3A0x8f898a45e70db8ea!2s10201%20Bee%20Oak%20Rd%2C%20Brandywine%2C%20MD%2020613!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694387226273!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade">
</iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking</strong> : With over 19 miles of marked trails, Cedarville State Forest is a haven for hikers of all skill levels. The trails offer scenic views of native plants and wildlife.</li>
<li><strong>Picnicking</strong> : There are designated areas with tables where you can enjoy a meal surrounded by nature.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing</strong> : Bring your fishing pole and try your luck in the ponds stocked with bluegill, bass, and catfish.</li>
<li><strong>Nature and Wildlife Watching</strong> : Be on the lookout for deer, turkey, fox, and a variety of bird species.</li>
<li><strong>Horseback Riding</strong> : Certain trails are designated for equestrian use. Just remember to bring your own horse!</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>Spring (late April to early June) and fall (September to October) are ideal for visiting Cedarville State Forest. The temperatures are mild, the forest is teeming with life, and the colors of the changing foliage (especially in the fall) make for a picturesque environment.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p>Cedarville is perfect for families. Children can learn about nature, enjoy open spaces, and participate in ranger-led programs (available seasonally). The campground is also pet-friendly, but remember to keep dogs on a leash at all times and clean up after them.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tent Sites</strong> : These basic sites are equipped with a picnic table and fire ring.</li>
<li><strong>RV Sites</strong> : While there are no hookups, there are designated spots for RVs with level grounds.</li>
<li><strong>Group Camping Areas</strong> : These are perfect for larger gatherings or events.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities</strong>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Restrooms and shower facilities</li>
<li>Potable water sources</li>
<li>Picnic areas with tables and grills</li>
<li>Playground for children</li>
<li>Dump station for RVs</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips-specific-to-the-campground">Safety Tips Specific to the Campground</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife</strong> : Remember, you are in their home. Always observe from a distance, do not feed them, and secure your food.</li>
<li><strong>Ticks and Bugs</strong> : Wear insect repellent and check for ticks after hiking or spending time in wooded areas.</li>
<li><strong>Fire Safety</strong> : Only start fires in designated areas or rings. Always put out fires completely before leaving or sleeping.</li>
<li><strong>Stay on Marked Trails</strong> : It’s easy to get lost in the forest. Stay on marked trails and always let someone know where you’re going.</li>
<li><strong>Weather</strong> : Be prepared for sudden weather changes, especially if you’re camping in transitional seasons.</li>
<li><strong>Water Safety</strong> : If you’re fishing or near water bodies, always supervise children and be cautious of slippery banks.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Cedarville State Forest in Maryland is a delightful destination for anyone looking to immerse themselves in nature. Whether you’re a seasoned camper or a first-timer, the forest’s beauty and serenity will surely captivate you. Remember to always follow the safety guidelines to ensure a memorable and enjoyable experience. Happy camping!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only.For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly.Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>USA, Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/cedarville-state-forest.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rocky Gap State Park Campground, Maryland, USA</title>
  <link>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/rocky-gap-state-park.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/https:/marylandroadtrips.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/MRT-Lake-Habeeb.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption"><a href="https://marylandroadtrips.com/design-your-perfect-escape-at-rocky-gap-state-park/">Photo Credit: Colleen Mulvihill </a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Rocky Gap State Park, nestled in the heart of Maryland, is a premier destination for nature enthusiasts, families, and campers alike. Whether you’re an experienced camper or a beginner looking for a refreshing escape, this picturesque state park offers a myriad of activities and experiences to create lasting memories.</p>
<p>Located on over 3,000 acres, Rocky Gap State Park is an epitome of tranquility, with the 243-acre Lake Habeeb at its heart. The captivating “blue waters” of the lake, contrasted against the thickly forested mountainside, are a sight to behold and offer a serene backdrop for an adventurous camping trip.</p>
<p><strong>Address:</strong> 17600 Campers Hill Drive, Flintstone MD 21530, Ph. No.&nbsp;443-603-6324</p>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://dnr.maryland.gov/publiclands/pages/western/rockygap.aspx">Official Maryland Department of Natural Resources Page for Rocky Gap State Park</a></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3068.9799691271523!2d-78.64467522402346!3d39.71763287156056!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89ca60310295cc77%3A0x58d0a77aab302d3!2s17600%20Campers%20Hill%20Dr%2C%20Flintstone%2C%20MD%2021530!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1694386775827!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade">
</iframe>
<section id="things-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-do">Things to Do</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> With over 15 miles of trails, hikers can choose from a variety of difficulty levels. The ‘Canyon Overlook Trail’ offers a breathtaking view of the gorge.</li>
<li><strong>Water Activities:</strong> Lake Habeeb offers swimming beaches, fishing opportunities (trout, catfish, and panfish, to name a few), and boating. Rent a canoe, kayak, or paddleboat and explore the lake’s beauty.</li>
<li><strong>Nature Programs:</strong> Engage in interpretative programs offered by park naturalists, from guided hikes to talks about local wildlife.</li>
<li><strong>Bird Watching:</strong> For avian enthusiasts, the park is home to numerous bird species, including the rare bald eagle.</li>
<li><strong>Hunting:</strong> During hunting seasons, designated parts of the park are open to hunting.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="best-time-of-the-year-to-visit">Best Time of the Year to Visit</h2>
<p>While Rocky Gap is open year-round, the <strong>spring and fall</strong> are particularly spectacular. Spring blossoms and fall foliage make for captivating vistas. However, summer remains popular for water activities and camping, with temperatures conducive for outdoor fun.</p>
</section>
<section id="family-and-pet-friendliness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-and-pet-friendliness">Family and Pet Friendliness</h2>
<p><strong>Family-friendly:</strong> Absolutely! Rocky Gap is perfect for families, with a range of activities suitable for all ages – from playgrounds for the little ones to fishing for the grown-ups.</p>
<p><strong>Pet-friendly:</strong> Yes, pets are allowed in certain camping loops. Always remember to keep your pets on a leash and clean up after them to maintain the park’s pristine condition.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-campsites-and-amenities">Types of Campsites and Amenities</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Standard Campsites:</strong> Ideal for tents and smaller RVs.</li>
<li><strong>Electric Hookup Campsites:</strong> Perfect for RV campers.</li>
<li><strong>Mini Cabins:</strong> For those who prefer a more structured setting without the hassle of pitching a tent.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Amenities</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Bathhouses with hot showers and flush toilets</li>
<li>Camp store for essentials and firewood</li>
<li>Picnic tables and fire rings at each site</li>
<li>Playground facilities</li>
<li>Dump station for RVs</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips">Safety Tips:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> While the park is home to various wildlife, it’s essential to maintain a distance. Do not feed or approach animals.</li>
<li><strong>Ticks and Mosquitoes:</strong> Use insect repellent and check for ticks daily, especially after hiking.</li>
<li><strong>Campfires:</strong> Only start fires in designated rings or grills. Ensure the fire is completely out before leaving.</li>
<li><strong>Hiking:</strong> Stay on designated trails, wear appropriate footwear, and always inform someone if you’re going on a long hike.</li>
<li><strong>Swimming:</strong> Only swim in designated areas and always supervise children.</li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Rocky Gap State Park offers a unique blend of serenity, adventure, and natural beauty. Whether you’re looking for a peaceful retreat or a series of adventures, this is the place to be. Always remember to respect nature, keep safety a priority, and leave no trace to ensure that the park remains a sanctuary for generations to come.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The content provided in these blog posts is for general informational purposes only. For the latest and most accurate information, we strongly recommend visiting the official website or contacting campground officials directly. Reliance on any information from this blog is solely at your own discretion.</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>USA, Maryland</category>
  <guid>https://www.outdoorsyindians.com/camping/usa/maryland/rocky-gap-state-park.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
