<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Outdoorsy Indians - General Articles</title>
<link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Our blog posts contain easy-to-follow guides, friendly gear reviews, and inspiring tales from everyday adventurers on hiking, camping, kayaking, and more.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Navigating the Western Ridge and Valley Trail Loop of Rock Creek Park: A Hiker’s Perspective</title>
  <dc:creator>Swati Gaikwad</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/jkrwVTK.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" data-group="western-ridge" alt="Old stone bridge on western ridge trail."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Western Ridge and Valley Trail Loop of Rock Creek Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Hiking, for me, offers a harmonious escape from the demands of daily life. One balmy morning in June, we set forth on the Western Ridge and Valley Trail Loop in the tranquil embrace of Rock Creek Park, Maryland. This scenic trail encompasses a 3.8-mile loop.</p>
<p>Accessibility is a notable advantage, as this trail is easily reachable via public transportation. We opted for the Red Line metro, specifically the Van Ness station, which added an additional 2 miles to our hike. There is also a parking lot available at the trailhead with ample space.</p>
<p>We began our hike at the parking lots near the southernmost point, following a clockwise direction. Reflecting on it, I believe it was the right choice. Although the trail app I employ categorizes it as ‘easy,’ I would personally classify it as more ‘moderate.’ While the Western Ridge segment felt undemanding, the Valley Trail portion presented its share of challenges. At times, it narrows and abounds with tree roots to navigate.</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/946kSg8.jpeg" class="img-fluid" data-group="western-ridge" alt="western ridge trail"> <img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/UTUcBE5.jpeg" class="img-fluid" data-group="western-ridge" alt="western ridge trail"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/sRmxKNl.jpeg" class="img-fluid" data-group="western-ridge" alt="western ridge trail"> <img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/hbyCUSq.jpeg" class="img-fluid" data-group="western-ridge" alt="western ridge trail"></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>During our hike, we embarked on a side trail, which added an adventurous element. This path was narrow, winding, rocky, and covered with roots, making it somewhat precarious, especially given its proximity to a slope leading to the creek. A stumble or slip could be unsettling.</p>
<p>The hike featured several uphill sections and a few tricky spots in terms of footing in the latter half. We relied on our phones to stay on the trail, and even then, we had to adjust our course a few times. Along the way, we passed by a horse center, offering a unique opportunity to see horses on a city trail.</p>
<p>In sum, it was a pleasurable hike that commenced with a satisfying climb through the woods and offered enchanting river vistas in the second half. Remember to bring an ample supply of water, snacks, and bug spray to enhance your experience.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/https:/i.imgur.com/YgnKLcZ.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-group="western-ridge" alt="western ridge trail"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Western Ridge and Valley Trail Loop of Rock Creek Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Trail head map:</p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m14!1m8!1m3!1d24822.856012299726!2d-77.0678552!3d38.9500951!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x89b7c83154a8040f%3A0x62726656bd4276eb!2sWestern%20Ridge%20Parking!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1695131215597!5m2!1sen!2sus" width="100%" height="450" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen="" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade">
</iframe>
<p><strong><a href="https://instagram.com/curios_wanderer?utm_source=qr&amp;igshid=MzNlNGNkZWQ4Mg==">Follow Swati Gaikwad on Instagram and witness her fantastic journey in the outdoors.</a></strong></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Hiking</category>
  <category>Rock Creek Park</category>
  <category>Real-life Experiences</category>
  <category>Inspirational Stories</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/008-00-western-ridge-and-valley-trail-loop/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/jkrwVTK.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>City Serenity: The Melvin C. Hazen Trail Experience</title>
  <dc:creator>Swati Gaikwad</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/Ki2Pv7r.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" data-group="melvin-hazen" alt="A portion of the Melvin C. Hazen Trail"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The Melvin C. Hazen Trail</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This year, I set my sights on exploring the trails nestled in the heart of the bustling cities within the District of Columbia, Maryland, and Virginia (DMV area). A dear friend encouraged me to document these urban adventures through blogging, with the goal of offering fellow enthusiasts a glimpse into these distinctive hikes and trails.</p>
<p>On one wintry weekend, as part of my ongoing city exploration series, I embarked on the Melvin C. Hazen Trail. Nestled within the urban landscape, this trail offers a delightful slice of nature that has the uncanny ability to make you feel as though you’ve left the city far behind. The rustic trailhead can be found at Melvin C. Hazen Park, setting the stage for a captivating journey.</p>
<p>To make this experience even more immersive, we decided to rely on public transportation. Our starting point was the Cleveland Metro Station, conveniently located on the red line of the D.C. metro system. From there, we ventured northward to commence our adventure.</p>
<p>The Melvin C. Hazen Trail is a modest 1-mile out-and-back trail, adorned with several enchanting and easy stream crossings, facilitated by stepping stones and fallen trees. It’s worth noting that during periods of elevated water levels, the stream may overflow, necessitating waterproof hiking shoes. Fortunately for us, this particular outing took place during the winter, sparing us from such concerns.</p>
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/7vIMb8I.jpg" class="img-fluid" data-group="melvin-hazen"></p>
<p>The trail is well-marked and falls under the category of easy hikes. While I hesitate to classify it as a true hike due to its relatively short distance, it offers a picturesque walk that effortlessly transports you away from the city bustle. It’s an accessible escape into tranquility and nature.</p>
<p>Melvin C. Hazen Trail also enjoys a reputation as a haven for bird nesting and birdwatching. Thus, a return visit during the spring or summer promises to be a birdwatcher’s paradise.</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/B7it08m.jpg" class="img-fluid" data-group="melvin-hazen"></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/rjBl7Ft.jpg" class="img-fluid" data-group="melvin-hazen"></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>As part of my ongoing city exploration project, I’m gearing up to elevate the challenge by extending the journey to Rock Creek Park. Fortunately, the Melvin C. Hazen Trail conveniently provides access to the Rock Creek Trail, opening up exciting possibilities for future adventures. I invite you to stay tuned for further updates as I continue to uncover the hidden gems within our urban landscapes.</p>
<p>Trail Map link:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nps.gov/places/reservation-630.htm">https://www.nps.gov/places/reservation-630.htm</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://instagram.com/curios_wanderer?utm_source=qr&amp;igshid=MzNlNGNkZWQ4Mg==">Follow Swati Gaikwad on Instagram and witness her fantastic journey in the outdoors.</a></strong></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Hiking</category>
  <category>Melvin C. Hazen Trail</category>
  <category>Real-life Experiences</category>
  <category>Inspirational Stories</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/007-00-hiking-melvin-c-hazen-trail/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/Ki2Pv7r.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hiking the Capital Crescent Trail: Urban Nature Retreat</title>
  <dc:creator>Swati Gaikwad</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/006-00-hiking-the-capital-crescent-trail/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/006-00-hiking-the-capital-crescent-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/239HeOr.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="A portion of the Capital Crescent Trail along the water body"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Capital Crescent Trail</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In the midst of the bustling urban life, I often seek solace and refuge in the serene embrace of nature during my hikes. Today, I’d like to share my recent adventure on the Capital Crescent Trail, a picturesque walking path that gracefully spans between two vibrant cities: Bethesda, Maryland, and Georgetown, Washington, D.C. This captivating trail extends over 7.0 miles, offering a point-to-point journey.</p>
<p>Our chosen route led us from Bethesda to Georgetown, presenting a delightful downhill course. The trail itself boasts a level terrain, cherished by runners, hikers, and cycling enthusiasts alike. While the initial 2.5 miles can be bustling on weekends, teeming with bikers and walkers, it gradually gives way to a quieter and more secluded path. Along the way, intermittent views of a winding river that flows parallel to the trail unfold.</p>
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/006-00-hiking-the-capital-crescent-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/8xZqmtL.jpeg" class="img-fluid" alt="Another portion of the Capital Crescent Trail"></p>
<p>What truly amazed us was the trail’s ability to maintain an oasis of tranquility amidst the urban surroundings, effectively drowning out the noise of city traffic. The three-hour trek to complete the trail left us exhausted but deeply fulfilled.</p>
<p>One of the trail’s distinct charms lies in the array of restaurants lining its trail heads. These proved to be a welcome sight for us, especially after a hearty meal at the first eatery we encountered.</p>
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/006-00-hiking-the-capital-crescent-trail/https:/i.imgur.com/NPPZLmC.jpeg" class="img-fluid" alt="An overlook point on the Capital Crescent Trail."></p>
<p>Accessibility to the trail is a breeze, with convenient public transportation options. Personally, I opted for the metro, traveling to Bethesda and then making my way to the trailhead. On the return journey, I disembarked at Rosslyn station, situated merely a mile from the trail’s conclusion.</p>
<p>For those who wish to customize their hiking experience, the trail is ingeniously designed with multiple entry points, offering ample parking facilities. It’s an adventure that beckons a return visit—a prospect I eagerly anticipate in the rich tapestry of city life.</p>
<p><strong>Trail Map</strong></p>
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=16MDKEsZSFnV1fdp3PPyEG7saVgggZkwG&amp;ehbc=2E312F" width="100%" height="480">
</iframe>
<p><strong><a href="https://instagram.com/curios_wanderer?utm_source=qr&amp;igshid=MzNlNGNkZWQ4Mg==">Follow Swati Gaikwad on Instagram and witness her fantastic journey in the outdoors.</a></strong></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Hiking</category>
  <category>Capital Crescent Trail</category>
  <category>Real-life Experiences</category>
  <category>Inspirational Stories</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/006-00-hiking-the-capital-crescent-trail/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://i.imgur.com/239HeOr.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Build a Campfire</title>
  <dc:creator>Rohit Farmer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/campfire-axe.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="A photo of a campfire in the woods with an axe next to it."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Photo by Elvis Bekmanis on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Building a campfire can be both a skill and an art. Whether camping in the wilderness or just wanting a cozy fire in your backyard, understanding the basics is essential for safety and efficiency. Here’s a step-by-step guide to help you build the perfect campfire.</p>
<section id="choose-a-safe-location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choose-a-safe-location">1. Choose a Safe Location</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ensure the spot is away from tents, trees, and shrubs.</li>
<li>Check for overhead branches that could catch fire.</li>
<li>If there’s an existing fire pit, use it. If not, clear a 10-foot diameter area down to the soil.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="prepare-the-ground" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prepare-the-ground">2. Prepare the Ground</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/dam/van_dragt_041117_0003_fire_ring.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A metal or stone fire ring"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A metal or stone fire ring. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Dig a shallow pit about a foot deep in the center of your cleared area. This will contain the fire and keep it from spreading.</li>
<li>Surround the pit with a circle of rocks. This serves as a wind barrier and a boundary for your fire.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="gather-materials" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gather-materials">3. Gather Materials</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/dam/van_dragt_041117_0008_fuel.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A photo of tinder, kindling, and firewood for building a campfire."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Tinder, kindling, and firewood. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are three main types of materials you need for a fire:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tinder:</strong> Small, dry materials that ignite easily. Examples are dry grass, leaves, paper, or cotton balls.</li>
<li><strong>Kindling:</strong> Small sticks and twigs, usually less than a finger’s width. They catch fire easily from the tinder.</li>
<li><strong>Firewood:</strong> Larger logs and branches. Once the fire is going strong, these will be your primary fuel source.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="constructing-the-fire" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="constructing-the-fire">4. Constructing the Fire</h2>
<p>There are various methods to build a fire, but two of the most popular ones are the “teepee” and the “log cabin.”</p>
<section id="teepee-method" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="teepee-method">Teepee Method</h3>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2015/06/P3120269.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A teepee campfire configuration"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Teepee campfire configuration. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li>Place a small pile of tinder in the center of your pit.</li>
<li>Arrange your kindling in a teepee shape over the tinder.</li>
<li>Add a larger layer of kindling around the first, followed by your smallest pieces of firewood.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="log-cabin-method" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="log-cabin-method">Log Cabin Method</h3>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2015/06/P3120251.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Log cabin campfire configuration. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ol type="1">
<li>Start with a small pile of tinder in the center.</li>
<li>Place two pieces of kindling parallel to each other on opposite sides of the tinder.</li>
<li>Add two more pieces on top, perpendicular to the first two.</li>
<li>Continue in this manner, building up like a log cabin, with the larger firewood forming the outer layers.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="lighting-the-fire" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lighting-the-fire">5. Lighting the Fire</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/dam/van_dragt_041117_0199_igniting_a_campfire.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lighting the fire using a ferro rod."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Lighting the fire using a ferro rod. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Light the tinder using a match or lighter. If you’re using the teepee method, the flames will rise, igniting the kindling and then the firewood.</li>
<li>If you’re using the log cabin method, you may need to add some additional tinder and kindling as the fire grows to ensure it spreads to the logs.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="maintaining-the-fire" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maintaining-the-fire">6. Maintaining the Fire</h2>
<ul>
<li>Add firewood as needed. Always place, don’t throw, to avoid scattering embers.</li>
<li>Rearrange logs occasionally using a stick or poker to ensure good airflow.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="putting-out-the-fire" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="putting-out-the-fire">7. Putting Out the Fire</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/https:/www.rei.com/dam/van_dragt_041117_0216_extinguishing.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A woman putting out the campfire with a bucket of water."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Put out the fire with water. Photo credit: REI</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Let the fire burn down well before you intend to put it out.</li>
<li>Pour water slowly over the fire to douse the flames. Be prepared for steam.</li>
<li>Stir the ashes with a stick to ensure all embers are wet.</li>
<li>Feel with your hand above the wet ashes to ensure there’s no heat left. (Never touch directly.)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="safety-tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-tips">8. Safety Tips</h2>
<ul>
<li>Always keep a water source or fire extinguisher nearby.</li>
<li>Never leave a campfire unattended.</li>
<li>Avoid building fires on windy days.</li>
<li>Ensure your fire is completely out before leaving the site or going to sleep.</li>
</ul>
<p>With practice, building a campfire becomes second nature. Whether for warmth, cooking, or just ambiance, a well-made campfire can enhance any outdoor experience. Always prioritize safety and “Leave No Trace” principles to protect yourself and the environment.</p>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Camping</category>
  <category>Campfire</category>
  <category>How To</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/005-00-how-to-build-a-campfire/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/campfire-axe.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Camping 101: The Ultimate Guide to Camping for Beginners</title>
  <dc:creator>Rohit Farmer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/004-00-a-beginners-guide-to-camping/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/004-00-a-beginners-guide-to-camping/https:/storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/tents-camping-at-night.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="A night time scene of a campsite with multiple tents."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Photo by Tommy Lisbin on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Camping is not just one activity but an umbrella term encompassing various approaches to spending time outdoors. From the modern comforts of “glamping” to the rugged solitude of backcountry camping, there’s a style for everyone. Part 1 of this article delves into the various types of camping, their pros and cons, and what you might need for each. Part 2 dives into details of “Car Tent Camping,” the most common and beginner-friendly type of camping.</p>
<section id="part-1-types-of-camping" class="level1">
<h1>Part 1: Types of Camping</h1>
<section id="car-tent-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="car-tent-camping">Car Tent Camping</h2>
<p>Car tent camping is the most commonly recognized form of camping, involving driving to a designated campsite, often within a public campsite facility, and setting up a tent. Sites usually offer basic amenities like water, fire pits, and communal restrooms.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Easy for beginners, family-friendly, and usually safe with moderate preparation.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Can be crowded, has a limited sense of solitude, and is less adventurous.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Tent, sleeping bag, cooking stove or grill, basic survival kit.</p>
</section>
<section id="rv-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rv-camping">RV Camping</h2>
<p>Campers travel in a motorhome or camper trailer in RV (Recreational Vehicle) camping. Many RV parks offer electric hookups, Wi-Fi, and other modern conveniences.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Comfortable, accessible for all ages, and easy to travel to multiple sites.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Expensive initial cost, not as “close to nature,” can be challenging to navigate certain terrains.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> RV, RV-specific appliances, potentially a generator, and standard camping gear for outdoor activities.</p>
</section>
<section id="backpacking" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="backpacking">Backpacking</h2>
<p>Backpacking involves hiking into the wilderness carrying all that you’ll need for your trip on your back. This type of camping usually takes place far from roads and facilities.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Solitude, close to nature, physically challenging and rewarding.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Requires thorough planning and preparation, physically demanding, potential for danger is higher.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Lightweight tent or hammock, lightweight sleeping bag and pad, portable stove, water purification, multi-day food supply, a first-aid kit, and large enough backpack.</p>
</section>
<section id="glamping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="glamping">Glamping</h2>
<p>Short for “Glamorous Camping,” glamping offers the joys of being close to nature without sacrificing modern amenities like electricity, beds, and sometimes even Wi-Fi.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Comfortable, great for those hesitant about traditional camping, often unique accommodations like treehouses or yurts.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> It can be expensive, not as immersive, and availability can be limited.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Depends on the venue. Usually, accommodations and basic amenities are provided.</p>
</section>
<section id="canoekayak-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="canoekayak-camping">Canoe/Kayak Camping</h2>
<p>Kayak camping involves paddling to a campsite only accessible by water. You carry your camping supplies in your boat and camp along riverbanks or lakeshores.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Solitude, unique experience, an additional element of challenge and adventure.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Requires boating skills, limited gear capacity, and can be physically demanding.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Canoe or kayak, paddles, life vests, waterproof bags, and lightweight camping gear.</p>
</section>
<section id="survivalist-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="survivalist-camping">Survivalist Camping</h2>
<p>Survivalist camping is an extreme form of camping where you head into the wilderness with minimal gear, intending to procure your food and shelter with the skills you possess.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Ultimate form of immersion in nature, honing survival skills.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Potentially dangerous, requires extensive knowledge and experience, physically and mentally demanding.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Survival kit including a knife, fire starter, water purification, and emergency supplies.</p>
</section>
<section id="winter-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="winter-camping">Winter Camping</h2>
<p>As the name suggests, winter camping is conducted in winter conditions, often involving snowshoeing or cross-country skiing to the campsite. Specialized cold-weather gear is a must.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Solitude, beautiful snow-covered landscapes, unique challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> Cold temperatures, increased risk of danger, specialized gear required.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Four-season tent, winter-rated sleeping bag, snow gear, avalanche safety gear.</p>
</section>
<section id="bikepacking" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bikepacking">Bikepacking</h2>
<p>Similar to backpacking but with the aid of a bicycle. Great for covering longer distances and carrying more gear than traditional backpacking.</p>
<p><strong>Pros:</strong> Increased range, the adventure of mixing cycling and camping, carry more weight than backpacking.</p>
<p><strong>Cons:</strong> It requires good physical fitness, complex logistics, and bike maintenance skills are required.</p>
<p><strong>Gear:</strong> Bike, panniers or saddlebags, lightweight camping gear, bike repair kit.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The type of camping you choose will depend on your interests, skills, and what you hope to get out of the experience. Whether you’re looking for a comfortable weekend getaway or a challenging wilderness adventure, there’s a type of camping out there for everyone.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="part-2-car-tent-camping" class="level1">
<h1>Part 2: Car Tent Camping</h1>
<p>Car tent camping involves using your vehicle as part of your camping setup. Unlike backpacking/backcountry camping, where everything you need must be carried on your back, or RV camping, which comes with amenities, car tent camping means you can bring more equipment and supplies since your car serves as your storage and transportation. Typically, the tent is pitched next to, or sometimes even attached to, the vehicle.</p>
<section id="advantages-of-car-tent-camping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="advantages-of-car-tent-camping">Advantages of Car Tent Camping</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Convenience:</strong> Your car acts as a storage unit, making storing and accessing your belongings more accessible.</li>
<li><strong>Cost-Effective:</strong> Compared to RV camping or staying at a hotel, this is a budget-friendly option.</li>
<li><strong>Comfort:</strong> You can bring more amenities than you would with backpacking, like larger tents, cooking gear, and mattresses.</li>
<li><strong>Accessibility:</strong> Great for families with young kids or anyone who prefers not to hike long distances to a campsite.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="planning-your-trip" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="planning-your-trip">Planning Your Trip</h2>
<section id="choose-the-right-location" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choose-the-right-location">Choose the Right Location</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Campgrounds vs.&nbsp;Primitive Sites:</strong> While campgrounds offer amenities like toilets, showers, on-site electrical outlets, and sometimes even Wi-Fi, primitive or dispersed camping sites give you solitude and a more rugged experience. I recommend state park-managed campgrounds with bathroom complexes in their campsite loop for beginners. We have booked electric and non-electric sites, but always with a bathroom complex in our loop. We have young kids, so we try to be as close to the bathroom complex as possible.</li>
<li><strong>Regulations:</strong> Always research any restrictions or requirements for camping in your chosen area. Most managed state/national park campgrounds require an advanced booking. On popular destinations or during peak seasons, they may also require minimum days of booking. Many campgrounds, for example, Maryland State Park campgrounds, do not allow alcohol on the premises and have restrictions on which sites can be used with pets. Many state parks also do not allow inter-state firewood transportation, so you will need to source your firewood from the camp store.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="make-a-checklist" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="make-a-checklist">Make a Checklist</h3>
<p>From cooking gear to bug spray, making a list ensures you don’t forget anything crucial. Essentials often include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tent and its components</li>
<li>Sleeping bags and pads or air mattresses</li>
<li>Cooking gear and food supplies</li>
<li>Clothing suitable for all weather conditions</li>
<li>Navigation tools like maps or GPS</li>
<li>First Aid Kit and bug spray</li>
<li>Light sources: flashlights, lanterns, etc.</li>
<li>Cutting tools: knife, saw, axe, etc.</li>
<li>Cordage: paracord, banklines, etc</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Check out my previous article on <a href="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/001-00-essentials-for-outdoor-survival/">Essentials for Outdoor Survival</a>, which lists the essential items you might need in an outdoor survival situation. And here is the <a href="https://www.rei.com/learn/expert-advice/family-camping-checklist.html">camping checklist</a> by REI.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-gear" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-gear">The Gear</h2>
<section id="choosing-a-tent" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-a-tent">Choosing a Tent</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Size:</strong> Pick a tent that offers enough space for everyone. A “four-person tent” may be cramped for four adults plus gear. However, it is generally okay for two adults and two kids. It is always better to consult experts at an outdoor fitter store like REI on the gear you might need based on the number of occupants and the place you are going. However, if you know what you are looking for, then the Facebook marketplace is an excellent option to score some used gear cheaply. I bought my one and four-person tents from the Facebook marketplace that were barely used and a quarter of the price.</li>
<li><strong>Weather:</strong> Your tent should be appropriate for the seasons you’ll be camping in, and this is where you need to spend more time researching or taking expert advice. Even if your tent is spacious enough for you and the gear, it may not hold even for 15 minutes in a downpour or get blown away easily. My one-person tent by <a href="https://alpsmountaineering.com/lynx-1-person-gray-navy-mesh-tent.html">Alps Mountaineering</a> is sturdy enough to take a beating. However, my four-person <a href="https://www.coleman.com/tents-canopies/tents-by-style/sundome-4-person-camping-tent/SAP_2155788.html">Coleman Sundome</a> budget tent gives away within 15 mins in a downpour. I still use it but with an additional tarp on it.</li>
<li><strong>Ease of Setup:</strong> As a beginner, you might prefer a tent that’s easy to set up. But avoid buying those unbranded, easy-to-set-up pop-up tents from Amazon. They are cheaply made and flimsy and would not stand the slightest change in the weather.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sleeping-essentials" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sleeping-essentials">Sleeping Essentials</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sleeping Bag:</strong> Choose one that’s suited for the climate. For a beginner camper, a three-season sleeping bag is ideal. It will allow you to camp from Spring to Fall in most places. You can get sleeping bags either with synthetic or down-filling material. Synthetic bas are cheaper, bulkier, but would still work when wet. Down sleeping bags are more expensive and lighter but usually are not as effective when wet unless the down is treated with water repellents. I have a <a href="https://www.marmot.com/equipment/sleeping-bags/synthetic/trestles-elite-eco-20-sleeping-bag/AFS_889169471551.html">Marmot Trestles Elite Eco 20° Sleeping Bag</a>, which is a synthetic bag, but it’s only slightly heavier than an REI down bag, much cheaper, and is rated for three seasons. So, for three seasons of car camping, I have no complaints.</li>
<li><strong>Sleeping Pad or Air Mattress:</strong> Essential for insulation and cushioning as you should never sleep directly on the tent floor. First, it’s not comfortable. Second, the campgrounds are colder than you might expect, removing all the warmth the sleeping bag provides.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="cooking-and-food-storage" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cooking-and-food-storage">Cooking and Food Storage</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stove:</strong> A simple propane/butane stove often works well for beginners. If you are with family, then go for a double-burner stove. Coleman has several models to suit your budget. Ozark Trail, a budget brand from Walmart, can also be a good beginner choice.</li>
<li><strong>Cooler:</strong> Keeps perishables safe. Again, Coleman is a good budget option. The size of the cooler depends upon the number of people and meals that require the ingredients to be kept cold. We have a basic Coleman 70 qt cooler that I bought used from the Facebook marketplace, which serves us well for two nights. We usually keep eggs, bacon, milk (for the baby), frozen meats, soda, and juices in the cooler. For Ice, we freeze 300 ml plastic water bottles to form the bottom layer and put ice cubes in several zip-lock bags for the top. We also use reusable ice packs instead of ice cubes to avoid liquid spills once the ice melts. The advantage of using frozen water bottles is that there is no spillover after the ice melts, and you have drinkable water to use.</li>
<li><strong>Cookware:</strong> Basic pots, pans, and utensils are usually sufficient. For car camping, you do not need those high-end lightweight titanium cookware. We took our home cookware when we went on our first camping. However, over time, we have made a separate set of stainless steel and cast iron cookware dedicated to camping, always stored in our camping tote. We use reusable plastic plates, cups, and cutlery - we avoid one-time use of paper plates or cups to minimize the trash. However, if you are a first-time camper, it might be overwhelming to organize, cook, and clean your cookware in the camp bathroom/wash station, so carrying a few paper plates, cups, and plastic utensils might be more manageable.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tools-light-and-fire-source" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tools-light-and-fire-source">Tools, Light, and Fire Source</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cutting Tools:</strong> You must have a knife in your kitchen set. However, having a camp/bushcraft knife, such as a fixed blade full tang knife, is helpful in various situations like processing firewood, clearing vegetation, cutting cordage, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Cordage:</strong> Your tent should come with guy lines along with stakes. However, if you also carry a tarp as an extra layer over your tent or cover the dining area, you would need additional cordage. Paracords are the most popular type of cordage used in camping. Inexpensive generic paracords from Dollar Tree are more than enough for non-load-bearing tasks such as hanging a tarp or clothesline.</li>
<li><strong>Flashlights and Lanterns:</strong> Campgrounds become pitch dark on a moonless night. Therefore, a dedicated flashlight is essential to move around your campsite or go to the bathroom complex. I prefer headlamps over handheld flashlights. I also bring a battery-operated or oil lantern for the general illumination of the campsite.</li>
<li><strong>Fire Source:</strong> In your kitchen set, you must have a lighter for your propane stove. However, an alternative source, such as waterproof matches or a ferro rod, can be used as a backup.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="setting-up-your-campsite" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="setting-up-your-campsite">Setting Up Your Campsite</h2>
<section id="tent-placement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tent-placement">Tent Placement</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Level Ground:</strong> Look for a flat and moisture-free area for your tent. If you are in a state park-managed campground, they usually have a tent pad filled with stone dust, which is good for keeping dry and providing a level surface. You can check if your campsite has a tent pad or know while making a booking. I have pitched tents on both tent pads and the ground and now I prefer tent pads. They can take in a lot of rain without getting muddy, making it cleaner to pack up the tent without spending too much time scrapping off the sticky goo.</li>
<li><strong>Safety:</strong> Ensure you’re not too close to a cliff edge, river, or other potential hazards. Again, if you are in a state park-managed campground, the campsites are designed to keep these things in mind. However, I try not to be very close to the river to avoid insects and water animals crawling in our campsite and avoiding the danger of kids running into the water.</li>
<li><strong>Distance:</strong> Keep a safe distance from your car’s exhaust to avoid carbon monoxide poisoning and the fire ring. You may need to run your car if you want to use it to charge your cell phones or use a pump to inflate your sleeping pad, etc. And sparklings from the campfire can burn a hole in your tent if not setting the whole thing on fire.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="kitchen-area" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kitchen-area">Kitchen Area</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fire Safety:</strong> For the similar reason to keep your tent away from the fire ring, keep the cooking area away from the tent.</li>
<li><strong>Accessibility:</strong> It should be easily accessible but not so close that it attracts animals to your sleeping area. It should not be tricky in a state park as the campsites are small and everything is within accessible range. However, since the picnic table - where you would probably set up your kitchen - is not too far from your tent, keeping it clean all the time is essential not to attract animals to your site.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="general-tips" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-tips">General Tips</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Footprint:</strong> Consider laying a tarp under your tent for extra protection from moisture. You can buy a footprint specific to your tent model. However, they are expensive, and if you have a budget tent, then probably not worth it. I use cheap utility tarps from Dollar Tree as my tent footprint. They form an extra layer of moisture protection and prevent my tent from getting excessively dirty. And since they are cheap, I can throw them away if they get damaged or too dirty to bring back home.</li>
<li><strong>Tent Stakes:</strong> Ensure they are securely in the ground to handle wind. I always stake down my tent even if there is no wind. You never know when the weather might change and blow away your tent.</li>
<li><strong>Storage:</strong> Use your car for secure storage, but remember to keep food in animal-proof containers in an area with wildlife.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="safety-measures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-measures">Safety Measures</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Follow Campfire Rules:</strong> If campfires are allowed, use established fire rings and always have water and a shovel on hand.</li>
<li><strong>First Aid:</strong> Always have a basic First Aid Kit with enough supplies for the group.</li>
<li><strong>Prescription Medication:</strong> Don’t forget to take your prescription medication.</li>
<li><strong>Insects Repellent:</strong> Always carry an <a href="https://a.co/d/c4eCfMb">insect repellent</a> that you can apply on your skin. Read the dosage strength before leaving home, especially for children. We also carry an alternative, such as <a href="https://a.co/d/bUYCCGJ">citronella candles</a> and <a href="https://a.co/d/de6q8BE">mosquito-repellent coils</a>, to burn in the dining and hangout area.</li>
<li><strong>Wildlife:</strong> Store food, trash, and scented items such as toiletries properly to avoid attracting unwanted guests. While car camping, your car is the best place to store such items before you hit the hay at night.</li>
<li><strong>Leave No Trace:</strong> Follow the Leave No Trace principles to keep nature as pristine as you found it.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="packing-up" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="packing-up">Packing Up</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Check for Leftovers:</strong> Make sure you’re not leaving anything behind.</li>
<li><strong>Garbage:</strong> Always take your trash with you or dispose of it in designated areas. Most campgrounds have large trash bins at the exit.</li>
<li><strong>Site Condition:</strong> Aim to leave the site in as good or better condition than you found it.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Car tent camping can be an exciting and enjoyable way to connect with nature. The convenience of having a car nearby offers a camping experience that merges the best of comfort and the outdoors. Whether you are a solo adventurer or a family looking to spend quality time together, this guide should help you prepare for your first car tent camping trip.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-2-contents" aria-controls="callout-2" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update history
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-2" class="callout-2-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>2023-09-06 First draft</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>
</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Camping</category>
  <category>Types of Camping</category>
  <category>Car Tent Camping</category>
  <category>Beginner</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/004-00-a-beginners-guide-to-camping/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/tents-camping-at-night.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Beginner’s Guide to Standup Paddleboarding (SUP)</title>
  <dc:creator>Rohit Farmer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/003-00-a-beginners-guide-to-standup-paddleboarding/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/003-00-a-beginners-guide-to-standup-paddleboarding/https:/storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/dishant-khatri-sup.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="An Indian man on his knees on a standup paddleboard at Emerald Lake, Yoho National Park, British Columbia, Canada"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">That’s my friend Dishant Khatri on his SUP at Emerald Lake, Yoho National Park, British Columbia, Canada</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>This article is an extension of my previous post on “<a href="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/002-00-a-beginners-guide-to-kayaking/">A Beginner’s Guide to Kayaking.</a>” The motivation to pick this activity is the same as kayaking. To get more on the water and add another enjoyable physical activity.</em></p>
<p>Standup paddleboarding, often called SUP, is a fantastic way to explore the water, exercise, and enjoy the outdoors. Whether on a calm lake, a meandering river, or even catching some waves in the ocean, standup paddleboarding offers a versatile and enjoyable experience for people of all ages and fitness levels. If you’re new to the world of SUP, this beginner’s guide will help you get started on your paddleboarding journey.</p>
<section id="where-to-begin-and-how-to-gain-access-to-a-sup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-to-begin-and-how-to-gain-access-to-a-sup">Where to begin and how to gain access to a SUP?</h2>
<p>When you start, you may not want to buy a SUP. SUPs, even though they have a smaller footprint than kayaks, are also of multiple types, can be expensive, need storage space, and make arrangements to transport them to water. All these take some planning and investment. You also do not know if you would like it or want to continue it as a long-term hobby. If you are in Maryland or most states in the USA, you can rent SUPs during the boating season, usually from Memorial Day to Labor Day. However, before heading out on your own on a rented SUP, I recommend first taking lessons in a group setting. It’s safer and will set you on the right path to explore further. Group classes are fun and have a low entry bar. Everyone is in the same boat (data joke) and motivates each other. Various outdoorsy organizations, such as REI, conduct classes frequently throughout the year or as weather permits.</p>
<p>I started <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/9390/learn-to-stand-up-paddleboard-class">standup paddleboarding</a> and <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/5668/learn-to-kayak-class">kayaking</a> by participating in classes organized by REI. The classes were conveniently located near my home, the instructors were terrific, and the REI provided all the necessary equipment, including a SUP, personal floatation device (PFD; life jacket), and accessories like dry bags for phones, car keys, etc. Lessons were long enough to get some practice time on the water but not overwhelming or physically straining. I did two classes, one for SUP and the second for kayaking, and my group comprised people from a wide age and fitness range.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>These courses and tours will cost you some money, and I know for us Indians, especially those living in a foreign country, one of our primary goals is to save money. However, I encourage you to fork out a little money and gain these experiences while you still can, and trust me, it will be worth it. Do not wait for a friend who might give you a free lesson on a rental one day; those opportunities are hard to come by and are nothing compared to REI or similar classes.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="essentials" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="essentials">Essentials</h3>
<section id="before-hitting-the-water-youll-need-to-gather-the-essential-equipment" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="before-hitting-the-water-youll-need-to-gather-the-essential-equipment">Before hitting the water, you’ll need to gather the essential equipment:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Paddleboard: Choose a stable and beginner-friendly board. Wider and longer boards are generally more stable, making them ideal for beginners.</li>
<li>Paddle: Ensure you have a correctly sized paddle that suits your height.</li>
<li>Personal Flotation Device (PFD): Safety first! Always wear a PFD when paddleboarding, especially if you’re not a confident swimmer.</li>
<li>Leash: A leash connects you to your board, preventing it from drifting away if you fall.</li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>REI provides all the essential equipment if you join one of their classes. Most rental facilities also provide at least the PFD with the paddleboard. I have had experience of not getting a leash with a few rentals. If you are a beginner, it’s crucial to have a leash.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="choosing-the-right-location" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-the-right-location">Choosing the Right Location</h4>
<p>Selecting the right location is crucial for a positive SUP experience. As a beginner, opt for calm, flatwater areas like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lakes</li>
<li>Slow-moving rivers</li>
<li>Ponds</li>
<li>Sheltered bays</li>
</ul>
<p>Avoid strong currents, heavy boat traffic, and rough waves until you’ve gained more experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="safety-precautions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safety-precautions">Safety Precautions</h4>
<p>Safety should be your top priority. Here are some safety tips to keep in mind:</p>
<ul>
<li>Check the weather forecast and wind conditions before heading out.</li>
<li>Wear sunscreen and appropriate clothing, considering weather and water temperature.</li>
<li>Familiarize yourself with local regulations and waterway rules.</li>
<li>Let someone know your paddleboarding plans and estimated return time.</li>
<li>Practice falling and remounting your board in a controlled environment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="still-not-ready-to-buy-a-sup-but-you-want-to-continue" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="still-not-ready-to-buy-a-sup-but-you-want-to-continue">Still not ready to buy a SUP, but you want to continue</h2>
<p>Even after doing the “learn to standup paddleboard” class and a couple of rentals, if you are still unsure if you should buy your SUP for financial, storage, or any other reasons - similar to me - but you still want to continue. Invest in water shoes, a life jacket, and clothing for water activities. In 2023, I was planning to buy an inflatable standup paddle board and kayak hybrid that I could easily store and transport in my Honda Civic, but for several reasons, I could not. So I decided to buy a <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/187431/astral-e-ronny-pfd-mens">life jacket</a> that fit me well and had more features than the ones you get when you rent a boat. Those rental ones are basic and soaked in other people’s sweat, which I find gross, even for a few hours. In addition to my life jacket, I also own a pair of <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/881347/nrs-kicker-remix-wetshoe-water-shoes-mens?redirect-pup=false">water shoes</a>, <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/188926/nrs-boaters-glove-mens?redirect-pup=false">boater’s gloves</a>, a <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/185196/rei-co-op-sahara-shade-hoodie-mens?redirect-pup=false">long-sleeved hooded shirt</a>, a bucket hat, and a pair of <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/202030/rei-co-op-sahara-convertible-pants-mens">convertible pants</a> for my water activities.</p>
<p>Clean gear that fits you well makes the activity more efficient and comfortable. You could spend more time thinking about and practicing your paddling skills than the gross rental life jacket, etc. It also makes you feel more invested in your hobby and will help you to sustain it longer.</p>
<p>Some other accessories that I find helpful are a <a href="https://a.co/d/gyEXzZ6">dry bag</a> to keep my car keys, wallet, snack, bandana, and a <a href="https://a.co/d/6A3BW0A">phone cover with floatation</a> to carry my phone around my neck to take photos. I like the flotation feature because a typical waterproof case can protect your phone from water, but it will sink if you drop it in the lake.</p>
</section>
<section id="so-you-want-to-take-the-plunge-and-buy-a-sup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-you-want-to-take-the-plunge-and-buy-a-sup">So, you want to take the plunge and buy a SUP</h2>
<p>Standup paddleboarding (SUP) has gained popularity over the years, leading to various paddle boards designed to suit different activities and conditions. Here are some of the main types of standup paddle boards:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>All-Around/Touring Boards:</strong> These are versatile boards suitable for various conditions, making them great for beginners. They’re stable, maneuverable, and can be used on calm water, small waves, and light touring.</li>
<li><strong>Surf SUPs:</strong> Explicitly designed for surfing, these boards are shorter and more maneuverable. They are often narrower and have a rocker (upward curve) in the nose and tail, allowing them to handle waves effectively.</li>
<li><strong>Flatwater/Race Boards:</strong> These boards are long and narrow, built for speed and efficiency on flat water. They have a pointed nose and a displacement hull design that helps them slice through the water more smoothly.</li>
<li><strong>Inflatable SUPs (iSUPs):</strong> These boards are made from durable, lightweight materials that can be inflated and deflated. They are great for portability and storage. Inflatable SUPs come in various styles, including all-around, touring, and racing.</li>
<li><strong>Yoga/Fitness SUPs:</strong> These boards are wide, stable, and designed with a soft top for comfort. They provide a stable platform for practicing yoga, fitness routines, and other on-water exercises.</li>
<li><strong>Fishing SUPs:</strong> These boards have features like extra stability, attachment points for fishing gear, and storage compartments. They’re designed for anglers who want to combine SUP with fishing.</li>
<li><strong>Whitewater SUPs:</strong> Built to handle river currents and rapids, whitewater SUPs are typically shorter, wider, and more robust to withstand the challenges of fast-moving water.</li>
<li><strong>Wind SUPs:</strong> These boards can attach a sail, allowing you to use wind power for propulsion. They’re designed for those who want to combine paddleboarding with windsurfing.</li>
<li><strong>Cruiser/Touring SUPs:</strong> Similar to touring boards, these SUPs are designed for longer-distance paddling and exploration. They often have additional attachment points for gear and are optimized for stability and tracking.</li>
<li><strong>Kids’ SUPs:</strong> Smaller, lighter boards designed for children. They provide a safe and fun introduction to paddleboarding for younger enthusiasts.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-Person SUPs:</strong> These oversized boards are designed to accommodate more than one paddler. They’re great for family outings or group activities.</li>
</ol>
<p>When choosing a standup paddleboard, consider your skill level, the type of water you’ll be using it on (calm lakes, rivers, ocean waves), and the activities you want to engage in (touring, surfing, fitness, etc.). Board size, shape, volume, and construction materials are important factors. Testing different types of SUPs or seeking advice from experienced paddleboarders before purchasing is a good idea.</p>
<section id="features-of-a-typical-sup" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="features-of-a-typical-sup">Features of a typical SUP</h3>
<p>A typical standup paddleboard (SUP) comprises various components and features contributing to its design, performance, and functionality. Here are the key features you’ll find on most SUPs:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Deck Pad:</strong> The deck pad is the cushioned area where you stand at the top of the board. It provides traction, comfort, and grip, helping you maintain balance and control.</li>
<li><strong>Carry Handle:</strong> A sturdy handle located in the center of the board makes it easier to carry the SUP to and from the water. Some boards may have multiple handles for different carrying options.</li>
<li><strong>Tie-Down Points:</strong> These are attachment points on the board’s surface where you can secure gear, such as a dry bag, cooler, or fishing equipment, using bungee cords or straps.</li>
<li><strong>Leash Attachment:</strong> A leash attachment point is typically located at the back of the board, allowing you to secure the leash to your ankle or calf. This prevents the board from drifting away if you fall off.</li>
<li><strong>Fin System:</strong> SUPs have fins that help with stability, tracking (maintaining a straight line), and maneuverability. The number and configuration of fins vary; some boards have a single center fin, while others have multiple fins.</li>
<li><strong>Nose and Tail:</strong> The board’s front (nose) and back (tail) have different shapes and designs depending on the board’s intended use. For example, surf SUPs have a more pointed nose for better wave performance, while touring boards have a rounder nose for better stability and tracking.</li>
<li><strong>Rails:</strong> Rails are the edges of the board that come into contact with the water. They can be soft or hard, rounded or sharp, and affect the board’s stability and maneuverability in different conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Volume and Thickness:</strong> The volume and thickness of a board affect its buoyancy and stability. Boards with more volume are more stable but can be slower, while boards with less volume are more maneuverable.</li>
<li><strong>Construction Material:</strong> SUPs can be made from various materials, including foam, fiberglass, epoxy, carbon fiber, and inflatable PVC. Each material has its weight, durability, performance, and cost characteristics.</li>
<li><strong>Deck Bungee System:</strong> Some boards, especially touring and all-around models, have a deck bungee system that provides additional storage space on the front of the board. This is useful for securing items like a life jacket or a dry bag.</li>
<li><strong>Rocker:</strong> The rocker refers to the curvature of the board from nose to tail. More rocker makes the board more maneuverable, while less rocker enhances speed and tracking.</li>
<li><strong>Tail Shape:</strong> Different tail shapes, such as square, pintail, or swallowtail, impact the board’s turning ability and stability.</li>
<li><strong>Vent Plug:</strong> Inflatable SUPs and some hard boards have a vent plug that allows air to escape and prevent damage from temperature changes or pressure.</li>
<li><strong>Graphics and Design:</strong> SUPs come in various colors, patterns, and graphics. While this doesn’t affect performance, it can add personalization and style to your board.</li>
</ol>
<p>Remember that the specific features of an SUP can vary based on the type of board, manufacturer, and intended use. Choosing a board that suits your skill level, preferred activities, and the conditions you’ll be paddling in is essential.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="basic-sup-techniques" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="basic-sup-techniques">Basic SUP Techniques</h2>
<section id="board-positioning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="board-positioning">Board Positioning</h3>
<ul>
<li>Stand beside your board in shallow water.</li>
<li>Place your paddle across the board, with one hand on the grip and the other on the blade.</li>
<li>Step onto the board, keeping your weight centered and knees slightly bent for balance.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="paddling-techniques" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paddling-techniques">Paddling Techniques</h3>
<ul>
<li>To move forward, dip the paddle into the water, pushing it back behind you while keeping your arms straight.</li>
<li>Twist your torso to paddle more efficiently, engaging your core muscles.</li>
<li>To steer, paddle on one side or the other.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="maintaining-balance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maintaining-balance">Maintaining Balance</h3>
<ul>
<li>Keep your feet shoulder-width apart for stability.</li>
<li>Look ahead and focus on a point to help maintain balance.</li>
<li>As a beginner, starting on your knees is okay until you feel confident standing up.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="tips-for-success" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tips-for-success">Tips for Success</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Start with a Lesson:</strong> Taking a beginner’s paddleboarding lesson can provide you with valuable guidance and safety tips from experienced instructors.</li>
<li><strong>Practice Makes Perfect:</strong> Don’t get discouraged if you wobble or fall initially. Paddleboarding is all about balance and takes time to master.</li>
<li><strong>Explore and Enjoy:</strong> Once you’ve gained confidence, explore different waterways and enjoy the scenic beauty around you. SUP is not just a workout; it’s a way to connect with nature.</li>
<li><strong>Respect the Environment:</strong> Always leave no trace and respect the environment you’re paddling in. Avoid disturbing wildlife and dispose of trash properly.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Standup paddleboarding is an accessible and enjoyable water activity for beginners and experienced paddlers alike. You can confidently embark on your SUP journey with the right equipment, knowledge, and a safety-first attitude. Remember to have fun, take in the beauty of your surroundings, and enjoy the tranquility of gliding across the water on your paddleboard. Happy paddling!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-3-contents" aria-controls="callout-3" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update history
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-3" class="callout-3-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>2023-09-01 First draft</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>SUP</category>
  <category>Paddling</category>
  <category>Water Sports</category>
  <category>Water Activities</category>
  <category>Beginner</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/003-00-a-beginners-guide-to-standup-paddleboarding/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/dishant-khatri-sup.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How To Kayak: The Ultimate Beginner’s Guide</title>
  <dc:creator>Rohit Farmer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/002-00-a-beginners-guide-to-kayaking/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/002-00-a-beginners-guide-to-kayaking/https:/storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/rohit-farmer-kayaking.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="Rohit Farmer on a kayak during his first learn to kayak class by REI at the Seneca Creek State Park, Gaithersburg, MD, USA"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">That’s me in my first learn to kayak class by REI at the Seneca Creek State Park, Gaithersburg, MD, USA</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I come from Allahabad (now Prayagraj), UP, India, the home to two of India’s most prominent rivers, the Ganges and Yamuna. However, besides doing a couple of paid boating trips on the rivers, I never got any opportunity for water sports - it was just not there. No boat houses for boat rentals no lessons on kayaking or canoeing. I would argue that it’s the same in most places in India. We can participate in water activities as tourists in certain places, but I do not know anyone who does that as a hobby or sport.</p>
<p>I naturally get attracted to water, and my long-time desire was to get involved in water sports - any type. Fortunately, I moved to Maryland in 2019, opening doors for me to take up water activities as a hobby. In this article, I will talk about my experience starting as a complete beginner, having no paddling/rowing experience.</p>
<section id="where-to-begin-and-how-to-gain-access-to-a-kayak" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-to-begin-and-how-to-gain-access-to-a-kayak">Where to begin and how to gain access to a kayak?</h2>
<p>When you start, you may not want to buy a kayak. Kayaks are of multiple types, can be expensive, need storage space, and make arrangements to transport them to water. All these take some planning and investment. You also do not know if you would like it or want to continue it as a long-term hobby. If you are in Maryland or most states in the USA, you can rent a vessel during the boating season, usually from Memorial Day to Labor Day. However, without knowing a thing about propelling watercraft, you may be hesitant or uncomfortable if not in danger. Therefore, I recommend taking classes on kayaking in a group setting first. That is how I got into kayaking and stand-up paddle boarding. Group classes are fun and have a low entry bar. Everyone is in the same boat (dad joke) and motivates each other. Various outdoorsy organizations, such as REI, conduct classes frequently throughout the year or as weather permits.</p>
<p>I started <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/5668/learn-to-kayak-class">kayaking</a> and <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/9390/learn-to-stand-up-paddleboard-class">stand-up paddle boarding (SUP)</a> by participating in classes organized by REI. The classes were conveniently located near my home, the instructors were terrific, and the REI provided all the necessary equipment, including a kayak, personal floatation device (PFD; life jacket), and accessories like dry bags for phones, car keys, etc. Lessons were long enough to get some practice time on the water but not overwhelming or physically straining. I did two classes, one for kayaking and the second for SUP, and my group comprised people from a wide age and fitness range.</p>
<p>Besides beginner classes, REI also conducts tours of varying lengths and fitness requirements of popular attractions in nearby areas. For example, popular tours in Maryland are the <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/57261/wye-island-kayak-tour">Wye Island Kayak Tour</a>, <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/51817/dc-monuments-kayak-tour">DC Monuments Kayak Tour</a>, and <a href="https://www.rei.com/events/51859/ghosts-of-the-potomac-mallows-bay-kayak-tour">Ghosts of the Potomac: Mallows Bay Kayak Tour</a>. After doing a beginner class, a couple of such tours are an excellent way to practice while still being in a group and with experts who help you learn and rescue if needed. I highly recommend REI classes, tours, and other courses led by a professional organization in your area.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>These courses and tours will cost you some money, and I know for us Indians, especially those living in a foreign country, one of our primary goals is to save money. However, I encourage you to fork out a little money and gain these experiences while you still can, and trust me, it will be worth it. Do not wait for a friend who might give you a free lesson on a rental one day; those opportunities are hard to come by and are nothing compared to REI or similar classes.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="still-not-ready-to-buy-a-kayak-but-you-want-to-continue" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="still-not-ready-to-buy-a-kayak-but-you-want-to-continue">Still not ready to buy a kayak, but you want to continue</h2>
<p>Even after doing learn to kayak courses and going on a couple of guided tours, if you are still unsure if you should buy your kayak for financial, storage, or any other reasons - similar to me - but you still want to continue. Invest in water shoes, a life jacket, and clothing for water activities. In 2023, I was planning to buy an inflatable stand-up paddle board and kayak hybrid that I could easily store and haul in my Honda Civic, but for several reasons, I could not. So I decided to buy a <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/187431/astral-e-ronny-pfd-mens">life jacket</a> that fit me well and had more features than the ones you get when you rent a boat. Those rental ones are basic and soaked in other people’s sweat, which I find gross, even for a few hours. In addition to my life jacket, I also own a pair of <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/881347/nrs-kicker-remix-wetshoe-water-shoes-mens?redirect-pup=false">water shoes</a>, <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/188926/nrs-boaters-glove-mens?redirect-pup=false">boater’s gloves</a>, a <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/185196/rei-co-op-sahara-shade-hoodie-mens?redirect-pup=false">long-sleeved hooded shirt</a>, a bucket hat, and a pair of <a href="https://www.rei.com/product/202030/rei-co-op-sahara-convertible-pants-mens">convertible pants</a> for my water activities.</p>
<p>Clean gear that fits you well makes the activity more efficient and comfortable. You could spend more time thinking about and practicing your paddling skills than the gross rental life jacket, water shoes, etc. It also makes you feel more invested in your hobby and will help you to sustain it longer.</p>
<p>Some other accessories that I find helpful are a <a href="https://a.co/d/gyEXzZ6">dry bag</a> to keep my car keys, wallet, snack, bandana, and a <a href="https://a.co/d/6A3BW0A">phone cover with floatation</a> to carry my phone around my neck to take photos. I like the flotation feature because a typical waterproof case can protect your phone from water, but it will sink if you drop it in the lake.</p>
</section>
<section id="so-you-want-to-take-the-plunge-and-buy-a-kayak" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-you-want-to-take-the-plunge-and-buy-a-kayak">So, you want to take the plunge and buy a kayak</h2>
<p>There are several different types of kayaks, each designed for specific purposes and environments. Here are some of the most common types:</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p></p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><span class=""><strong>Tracking</strong> in kayaking refers to the kayak’s ability to maintain a straight course through the water without excessive veering or wandering off course. A kayak with good tracking capabilities will travel in a straight line when paddled, requiring less corrective effort from the paddler to keep it on course.</span></div></div>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Recreational Kayaks:</strong> These kayaks are ideal for beginners and casual paddlers. They are stable, easy to maneuver, and typically have a larger cockpit for easy entry and exit. Recreational kayaks are great for calm waters like lakes, slow rivers, and calm coastal areas.</li>
<li><strong>Touring Kayaks:</strong> Touring kayaks are designed for longer journeys and offer better tracking and efficiency in the water. They have more storage space for gear and are suitable for exploring larger bodies of water like lakes, bays, and coastal areas.</li>
<li><strong>Sea Kayaks:</strong> Similar to touring kayaks, sea kayaks are designed for open waters, including oceans and rougher conditions. They have a longer hull and are often equipped with features like rudders or skegs to improve tracking and stability.</li>
<li><strong>Sit-on-Top Kayaks:</strong> These kayaks have an open design where the paddler sits on top rather than inside a cockpit. They’re popular for recreational use, warm climates, and activities like fishing and snorkeling. They’re easy to get on and off and self-draining.</li>
<li><strong>Inflatable Kayaks:</strong> Inflatable kayaks are portable and convenient, as they can be deflated and packed for easy transport. They are versatile and suitable for calm waters, making them a good option for those with limited storage space.</li>
<li><strong>Whitewater Kayaks:</strong> Designed for navigating swift rivers and whitewater rapids, whitewater kayaks are shorter and more maneuverable. They often have a lower volume and specialized features to handle the challenges of fast-moving water.</li>
<li><strong>Playboats:</strong> Playboats are a type of whitewater kayak designed for performing tricks and maneuvers in waves and rapids. They are shorter and highly maneuverable, allowing kayakers to engage in freestyle moves.</li>
<li><strong>Crossover Kayaks:</strong> These kayaks aim to combine features from different types, making them versatile for various conditions. They might have the stability of a recreational kayak and the efficiency of a touring kayak, for example.</li>
<li><strong>Folding Kayaks:</strong> Folding kayaks are made from materials like fabric and metal frames, allowing them to be folded up and stored compactly. They’re great for adventurers who want to explore remote areas and have limited transportation options.</li>
<li><strong>Surf Skis:</strong> Surf skis are long, narrow kayaks designed for speed and efficiency in open water. They are often used in competitive paddling and are suitable for experienced kayakers.</li>
</ol>
<p>Before choosing a kayak, consider your skill level, intended activities, and the type of waters you’ll be exploring. Each kayak type has its advantages and limitations, so it’s important to pick one that suits your preferences and needs.</p>
<section id="features-of-a-typical-kayak" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="features-of-a-typical-kayak">Features of a typical kayak</h3>
<p>A typical kayak has several key features contributing to its performance, stability, and functionality. Here are the main components you’ll find on most kayaks:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hull:</strong> The hull is the bottom of the kayak that comes into contact with the water. It can be categorized into two main types: flat and rounded. Flat hulls offer more stability, while rounded hulls provide better maneuverability.</li>
<li><strong>Cockpit:</strong> The cockpit is the opening where the kayaker sits. It can vary in size and shape depending on the type of kayak. Sit-on-top kayaks have an open cockpit, while traditional kayaks have a closed cockpit with a cover.</li>
<li><strong>Deck:</strong> The deck is the top surface of the kayak. It often features rigging, bungee cords, or straps to secure gear and accessories. On closed-cockpit kayaks, the deck also includes a hatch for storage.</li>
<li><strong>Seat:</strong> The seat provides comfort for the paddler during long journeys. Some kayaks have adjustable seats to accommodate different body sizes and paddling styles.</li>
<li><strong>Footrests or Foot Pegs:</strong> These adjustable footrests or pegs provide support for your feet and help you apply leverage for powerful paddle strokes.</li>
<li><strong>Paddle:</strong> The paddle is the key tool for propelling the kayak through the water. Paddle length and blade shape can vary based on the paddler’s height and intended use.</li>
<li><strong>Bulkheads:</strong> Bulkheads are partitions inside the kayak that create separate storage compartments, typically in sea kayaks. They provide buoyancy and keep water out of the compartments.</li>
<li><strong>Hatch Covers:</strong> Found on sea kayaks and touring kayaks, hatch covers to seal the storage compartments to keep gear dry and prevent water from entering.</li>
<li><strong>Deck Rigging:</strong> Bungee cords or straps on the deck are used to secure items like dry bags, water bottles, and other accessories.</li>
<li><strong>Rudder or Skeg:</strong> These are features on some kayaks, particularly sea kayaks. A rudder is an adjustable fin at the stern that helps with steering in wind and currents, while a skeg is a fixed fin that aids tracking.</li>
<li><strong>Grab Handles:</strong> Handles located on the bow, stern, and sides of the kayak make it easier to transport the kayak to and from the water.</li>
<li><strong>Thigh Braces:</strong> Thigh braces are padded areas inside the cockpit that provide contact points for your thighs, helping with control and stability.</li>
<li><strong>Spray Skirt:</strong> A spray skirt is used with closed cockpit kayaks to seal off the cockpit and prevent water from entering. It’s especially useful in rough conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Paddle Leash:</strong> A paddle leash secures your paddle to the kayak to prevent it from floating away if you accidentally drop it.</li>
<li><strong>Safety Lines</strong>: These lines run along the perimeter of the kayak and provide a handhold for assisted rescues and self-rescue techniques.</li>
</ol>
<p>These features can vary based on the type of kayak and its intended use. Choosing a kayak with the right features for your skill level, preferred activities, and the water conditions you plan to encounter is important.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Embarking on your kayaking journey can be an incredibly rewarding experience. Whether you’re seeking adrenaline-pumping adventures or serene moments of tranquility, kayaking has something to offer for everyone. By selecting the right equipment, learning essential techniques, prioritizing safety, and respecting the environment, you’ll be well on your way to enjoying the wonders of this exciting water sport. So grab your paddle, embrace the water, and let the kayaking adventures begin!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-2-contents" aria-controls="callout-2" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update history
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-2" class="callout-2-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>2023-08-29 First draft</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Kayaking</category>
  <category>Paddling</category>
  <category>Water Sports</category>
  <category>Water Activities</category>
  <category>Beginner</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/002-00-a-beginners-guide-to-kayaking/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/rohit-farmer-kayaking.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Essentials for Outdoor Survival</title>
  <dc:creator>Rohit Farmer</dc:creator>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/001-00-essentials-for-outdoor-survival/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/001-00-essentials-for-outdoor-survival/https:/storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/bushcraft-shelter.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="Photo of a bushcraft shelter"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Photo by Caspian Dahlström on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Survival should not be the first thing to come to mind while thinking about the great outdoors - it should be fun, adventure, mesmerizing views, a star-filled night, the sound of a waterfall, encountering wildlife, and making memories with your loved ones. However, as soon as you step outside the comforts and protection of your house, you are subjected to the elements and unforeseen difficult situations. Therefore, heading out with some basic preparedness is always helpful, especially with a family, including small children. This post is inspired by the famous 5Cs of survivability and the <a href="https://www.nps.gov/articles/10essentials.htm">ten essentials</a> by the National Park Services. And I hope these essential principles serve as your compass, guiding you through the rugged terrain and helping you emerge victorious in the face of nature’s trials.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Important
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>No matter how many survival tools you have in your pack, if you can call emergency services, for example, 911 in the US or 100 in India, do that first. Nothing is better than letting trained professionals take care of the situation. However, while waiting for help and rescue to arrive, you can take some measures to ease the situation, for example, administering first aid, making a shelter to protect from the weather, making fire to keep the victim and yourself warm, etc.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="calmness-the-anchor-in-the-storm" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="calmness-the-anchor-in-the-storm">Calmness: the anchor in the storm</h2>
<p>First, if you are met with an unpleasant event, such as getting lost on the hiking trail or injured, do not panic. I know it’s harder done than said, and freaking out in the face of a disaster is natural - especially when your kids are involved. However, maintaining a sense of calmness is your greatest asset. Panic clouds judgment and impedes decision-making. Instead, take a deep breath and embrace the stillness within. Calmness allows you to assess your situation, consider your options, and formulate a rational plan. A calm mind can save your life even in the face of danger.</p>
</section>
<section id="first-aid-kit-treat-while-you-wait" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-aid-kit-treat-while-you-wait">First aid kit: treat while you wait</h2>
<p>A well-equipped first aid kit can be a lifesaver in any outdoor adventure. Accidents and injuries can happen unexpectedly, and being prepared with a first aid kit can make a significant difference in managing medical situations effectively. What a first aid kit should include depends on the nature of the activity and the people involved. Carrying a well-stocked first aid kit is a proactive step towards ensuring safety during outdoor expeditions. However, at a minimum, a good kit should include essential items like adhesive bandages, gauze pads, antiseptic wipes/creams, pain relievers, and any personal medications. Additionally, items such as a CAT tourniquet, splint materials, blister treatment, and compact emergency blankets are invaluable for addressing a variety of potential injuries.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="cutting-tools-for-crafting-and-survival" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cutting-tools-for-crafting-and-survival">Cutting: tools for crafting and survival</h2>
<p>A cutting tool, such as fixed blade knives, multitools, axes, and saws (all fall under this category), can make a significant difference in your attempt at survival. These tools can be used for opening a first aid kit, crafting shelter, procuring food, and processing wood for fire, amongst numerous other things. I always keep a small Swiss Army Knife in my car that goes to my day back or waist pack when I hit the trail or a park with kids. If needed, I also carry a bigger multitool with a plier and a small saw that adds more functionality without adding much weight to my pack. Besides multitools, a fixed blade full tang knife is essential while camping overnight. If you are car camping, you can carry all three. However, a fixed-blade knife would be more reliable while backpacking camping, especially for processing firewood.</p>
<p>While car camping, I carry an 11-inch foldable saw, a multitool, and a fixed-blade knife. When writing this post, I have not gone backpacking camping, so I am still determining what I will take. But it most likely is my Morakniv full-tang fixed blade knife.</p>
</section>
<section id="combustion-and-light-harnessing-the-power-of-fire" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="combustion-and-light-harnessing-the-power-of-fire">Combustion and light: harnessing the power of fire</h2>
<p>Fire is a primal force that has been humanity’s ally for millennia. It provides warmth, light, a means to cook food, and a psychological boost in challenging times. In your survival kit, carry fire-starting tools like a box of matches (waterproof if possible), lighter, ferro rod, etc. Setting things up on fire is relatively easy. However, building a good fire for keeping warm for an extended period or cooking food can take some skills. Therefore, learning and practicing the fire building - from gathering tinder to kindler to fule and creating a sustainable blaze is helpful and fun. In the wilderness, fire is more than survival; it symbolizes resilience and adaptability.</p>
<p>On day hikes, I usually carry a small Bic lighter; they hardly weigh and always work. I carry waterproof matches, Bic lighters (small and big), a Ferro rod, and some fire-starting cubes for car camping. Fire-starting cubes are excellent while camping. They are effortless and can reduce the burden of finding the right tinder and kindling material. I like to use them, especially on a cold morning when I want to get the fire going quickly, mostly on its own, while cooking my breakfast.</p>
<p>A campfire can keep you warm and cook your food, but it’s not luminous or portable enough to let you navigate the campsite, set up a shelter, or go to the bathroom. Therefore, you need a dedicated battery-operated light source, which could be as simple as your phone’s camera flash or a cheap flashlight from the Dollar Store or Walmart. However, having a headlamp is most versatile in its utility.</p>
</section>
<section id="cover-sheltering-yourself-from-the-elements" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cover-sheltering-yourself-from-the-elements">Cover: sheltering yourself from the elements</h2>
<p>Proper clothing is your first line of defense against the harsh realities of the wilderness. Dressing appropriately for the environment is crucial to regulate body temperature and prevent hypothermia or heatstroke. Layering is critical, as it allows you to adjust to changing conditions. Sturdy, comfortable footwear is a must to navigate rugged terrain and prevent blisters. Remember, in the wild, your clothing is not just an outfit; it’s your shield against nature’s challenges.</p>
<p>Besides clothing, tarps (rain fly), ponchos (rain gear), and tents form the second line of defense against the elements. These cover options shield you from rain, wind, and sun, providing a safe haven to rest and regroup. Whether you are setting up a makeshift shelter or using a compact tent, having the means to create a protective barrier against the wild is essential.</p>
<p>Depending on the weather forecast, I carry a lightweight poncho on a day hike, which can also be spread on the ground to sit or lie down. If I am not carrying my multipurpose poncho, I carry a lightweight waterproof ground sheet/blanket for lying down. I do not carry tarps or tents on a day hike. However, while car camping with family, I carry several tarps for extra rain cover over our tent and cooking area and one emergency poncho for each family member.</p>
</section>
<section id="container-securing-vital-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="container-securing-vital-resources">Container: securing vital resources</h2>
<p>A container – such as a water bottle – is handy for securing and transporting water. Water is paramount to survival, and having the means to collect and store it is non-negotiable. Containers can also be used to store edible plants, insects, or small game you might come across. Choose containers that are durable, leak-proof, and lightweight for easy portability.</p>
<p>For a short day hike, I usually carry two Smart (plastic) water bottles as they are lightweight, and I am not in danger of getting stranded for an extended period where I have to source water from my surroundings and purify it by boiling. However, if I am camping, I keep plastic water bottles/jugs as primary storage and a metal container, be it a water bottle (single-walled) or a kettle to boil the water. Of course, if you are backpacking, you will carry a kettle to boil the water for your ready-to-eat meals and coffee.</p>
<p>If you go to the beach, carry a double-walled insulated water bottle. It will add to the overall weight but keep your water cool even if you put it on the warm sand.</p>
</section>
<section id="cordage-your-versatile-lifeline" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cordage-your-versatile-lifeline">Cordage: your versatile lifeline</h2>
<p>Any type of heavy-duty or multi-purpose string falls under the category of cordage. From setting up shelter to crafting tools and traps, cordage is the lifeline that enables you to secure, tie, and create. Whether paracord, natural fibers, or improvised materials, having a good supply of cordage opens up a world of possibilities in the wild.</p>
<p>I am a big fan of paracords from Dollar Tree (25 ft) and Temu.com (100 ft) for setting up tarps over my tent and cooking area. I use the 100 ft cord for the tarp’s ridgeline and 25 ft cords for the guylines, and so far, they have reached even the most distant spread of trees around my campsites.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Paracords from Dollar Tree and Temu are cheap, but I would not trust them for critical load-bearing tasks. Even though they are sold as paracords, they do not have any load-bearing capacity rating. The rated 550 paracords should have a load-bearing capacity of 550 lbs.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Besides paracords, I also use tarred nylon twine #18 from Walmart’s fishing equipment section. They are also called banklines, and the famous one is #36. Bank lines are much cheaper than paracords and useful for crafts where you want to cut the cord and probably leave it in the wild. I use bank lines to make prusik knots to tension my tarp on the ridgeline.</p>
</section>
<section id="communications-and-navigation-your-way-to-call-for-help-and-find-your-way-around" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="communications-and-navigation-your-way-to-call-for-help-and-find-your-way-around">Communications and navigation: your way to call for help and find your way around</h2>
<p>I cannot move around in the USA without GPS on my phone, and probably it’s the same for you unless you have lived in the region for a very long time. Also, phone is the only quick way to call for help. Therefore, it goes without saying to keep the phone charged all the time with an active and sufficient calling and data plan. I also tend to download offline maps of the region I will be traveling to in case there is poor internet connectivity, which usually is many National Parks.</p>
<p>Besides Google Maps, I also install alternative navigation software that does not depend on the internet, such as OsmAnd+ or Organic Maps. I also recommend paper maps and a compass. However, I realize that only a few people can navigate using a paper map and a compass. It’s a skill worth taking up, and several outdoorsy organizations teach it, including your local REI store.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Since our mobile phones are such an integral part of our lives, in addition to keeping my phone in a sturdy phone case, I also carry a waterproof case with floatation that I can hang around my neck with lanyards while I am on the water either kayaking or stand up paddle boarding. Just keeping your phone in a waterproof casing is enough for the rain, but it will sink if it is dropped in the water. Therefore, a case with flotation capabilities is a must.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>While camping (with family), we also carry cheap walkie-talkie radios that kids can use while going to the bathroom or playing near the campsite. Unlike cell phones, radios within range do not need internet or communication towers to work.</p>
</section>
<section id="sanitizers-bug-spray-and-sunscreens-keep-the-germs-away-and-protect-your-skin" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sanitizers-bug-spray-and-sunscreens-keep-the-germs-away-and-protect-your-skin">Sanitizers, bug spray, and sunscreens: keep the germs away and protect your skin</h2>
<p>People say there is nothing called hygiene and counting calories while outdoors. However, getting sick while camping or returning home is not fun. Therefore, keep a small bottle of hand sanitizer. They are not heavy, and some hygiene won’t hurt.</p>
<p>Bugs are everywhere. You are invading their home, so they will not like it and might want to hurt you. So, insect repellents are a must. They protect you from the discomfort of insect bites and insect-borne diseases. Please check the recommended dosage and type of insect repellent for kids before heading out.</p>
<p>For bears, while camping or going on long hikes like in the Shenandoah National Parks, I always carry a bear spray can with me. However, before carrying a bear spray, check the park rules if they are allowed and learn how to use them before they are needed in action. Other nonchemical methods to deter a black bear, like a pressure horn or a jingle bell attached to your pack, let the bear know there are people around.</p>
<p>Beaches are not the only place you might need a splash of sunscreen. Depending upon where you are hiking, you might encounter long stretches of unshaded regions where you may need sun protection. Therefore, keep a small tube of sunscreen.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>Surviving in the outdoors demands respect for nature’s power and a deep understanding of your capabilities. In this article, I aimed to list the categories of tools and skills that will empower you to navigate challenges, make sound decisions, and harness the resources around you to ensure you are ready to take care of any unpleasant events for yourself and your family while enjoying the great outdoors. You can choose one tool per category or multiple, depending on the activity and the people involved. I try to be extra prepared with family and keep backup tools per category.</p>
<p>The purpose of this article was to prepare and make you think about what you might need in an outdoor survival situation. It is not to scare you or get paranoid about every little detail. For most outdoor activities, we are not far from help; therefore, don’t get too carried away thinking about survival and miss the beauty and enjoyment of the great outdoors. Otherwise, that would be self-defeating.</p>
<p><strong>Now get on, and I might meet you on the trail!</strong></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-4-contents" aria-controls="callout-4" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update history
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-4" class="callout-4-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>2023-08-25 First aid kit section added</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Survival</category>
  <category>First Aid</category>
  <category>Cutting</category>
  <category>Combustion</category>
  <category>Cover</category>
  <category>Container</category>
  <category>Cordage</category>
  <category>Communication</category>
  <category>Navigation</category>
  <category>Insect Repellent</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/posts/001-00-essentials-for-outdoor-survival/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Aug 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/posts/bushcraft-shelter.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
