<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Outdoorsy Indians - Things To Do</title>
<link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Check out our blog posts on outdoorsy things-to-do around the world.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.551</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do During Fall in Maryland, USA</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/usa/maryland-outdoors-fall/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/usa/maryland-fall-colors.webp" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Carl Schlabach on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Maryland, with its diverse landscapes, ranging from Appalachian foothills to the Chesapeake Bay shores, is a haven for outdoor enthusiasts, especially in the fall. As the leaves change colors and the air gets cooler, here are some of the top outdoorsy activities to do in Maryland during this enchanting season:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Hiking Amidst Fall Foliage:</strong> Maryland’s state parks and trails come alive with red, orange, and yellow hues.
<ul>
<li><strong>Cunningham Falls State Park:</strong> Besides the spectacular falls, there are various hiking trails that offer panoramic views of the vibrant foliage.</li>
<li><strong>Gathland State Park:</strong> Located on the Appalachian Trail, it’s an excellent spot for leaf peeping and historic sightseeing.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Camping Under the Stars: </strong>With cooler temperatures and fewer bugs, fall is an ideal time for camping.
<ul>
<li><strong>Green Ridge State Forest: </strong>Known for its rugged beauty, it offers numerous campsites and miles of trails.</li>
<li><strong>Assateague State Park: </strong>Camp by the beach and witness wild ponies roaming the sands.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Kayaking and Canoeing: </strong>Experience the serenity of paddling on Maryland’s waterways surrounded by autumn colors.
<ul>
<li><strong>Deep Creek Lake: </strong>Enjoy the crisp air and the sound of leaves rustling as you paddle.</li>
<li><strong>Antietam Creek: </strong>Known for its Civil War history and scenic beauty, it’s a perfect place for a fall paddle.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mountain Biking: </strong>The trails in Maryland offer a unique biking experience with the backdrop of fall colors.
<ul>
<li><strong>Schaeffer Farms Mountain Bike Trail:</strong> With various loops and terrains, it’s a treat for beginners and experts.</li>
<li><strong>Patapsco Valley State Park:</strong> It’s a favorite among mountain bikers, offering miles of trails through wooded areas.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Rock Climbing:</strong> For adrenaline junkies, Maryland’s cliffs provide a thrilling climbing experience.
<ul>
<li><strong>Carderock Recreation Area: </strong>Located by the Potomac River, it offers a range of climbing difficulties.</li>
<li><strong>Rocks State Park:</strong> Known for King and Queen Seat, a 190-foot rock outcrop, it’s a hotspot for climbers.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Horseback Riding: </strong>Traverse through the scenic trails of Maryland on horseback.
<ul>
<li><strong>Gunpowder Falls State Park:</strong> They offer guided horseback tours, allowing you to experience the park uniquely.</li>
<li><strong>River Valley Ranch:</strong> Located in Manchester, they provide trail rides through the picturesque countryside.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Fishing:</strong> The fall season brings a variety of fish species, making it a great time for anglers.
<ul>
<li><strong>Liberty Reservoir:</strong> A hotspot for large mouth bass, catfish, and crappie.</li>
<li><strong>Chesapeake Bay:</strong> Fall is the prime time for rockfish and bluefish.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Bird Watching:</strong> With the migration season in full swing, it’s a haven for bird enthusiasts.
<ul>
<li><strong>Blackwater National Wildlife Refuge:</strong> Home to bald eagles, ospreys, and a variety of waterfowl.</li>
<li><strong>Cape Henlopen State Park:</strong> Witness the fall hawk migration.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Zip Lining: </strong>Experience the thrill of zip lining amidst the beauty of fall.
<ul>
<li><strong>Sandy Spring Adventure Park:</strong> Glide through the trees, taking in the spectacular view below.</li>
<li><strong>Go Ape Treetop Adventure:</strong> Located in Rock Creek Regional Park, it offers an exhilarating treetop experience.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Orchard Walks:</strong> Stroll through apple orchards, picking fresh apples and enjoying the crisp autumn air.
<ul>
<li><strong>Baugher’s Orchard:</strong> Besides apple picking, enjoy a tractor-drawn wagon ride through the farm.</li>
<li><strong>Homestead Farm:</strong> Wander amidst rows of apple trees and pick fresh pumpkins.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Lighthouse Tours: </strong>Maryland’s coastline boasts some historic and picturesque lighthouses.
<ul>
<li><strong>Concord Point Lighthouse:</strong> Located in Havre de Grace, it offers panoramic views of the Susquehanna River and Chesapeake Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Drum Point Lighthouse: </strong>This cottage-style lighthouse offers guided tours in Solomons.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Scenic Train Rides: </strong>Experience the fall scenery from the comfort of a train car.
<ul>
<li><strong>Western Maryland Scenic Railroad:</strong> This steam-powered train ride, departing from Cumberland, offers a spectacular view of the Allegheny Mountains.</li>
<li><strong>Walkersville Southern Railroad:</strong> Travel through the Maryland countryside and along the Monocacy River, with dinner train options available.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Wildlife Photography: </strong>The changing seasons bring unique wildlife-viewing opportunities.
<ul>
<li><strong>Catoctin Mountain Park:</strong> Capture candid shots of deer, foxes, and birds against a backdrop of autumn leaves.</li>
<li><strong>Eastern Neck National Wildlife Refuge: </strong>A haven for migratory birds and native wildlife.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Hot Air Balloon Rides: </strong>See Maryland’s fall colors from a new perspective.
<ul>
<li><strong>Tailwinds Over Frederick: </strong>Experience the beauty of Frederick County’s landscapes from above.</li>
<li><strong>Friendship Hot Air Balloon Co:</strong> Based in West Friendship, they offer serene flights over the Howard County countryside.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Outdoor Farmers’ Markets: </strong>Fall brings a bounty of seasonal produce and artisan goods.
<ul>
<li><strong>Baltimore Farmers’ Market &amp; Bazaar:</strong> Maryland’s largest producers-only market with a range of fall produce, baked goods, and crafts.</li>
<li><strong>Bethesda Central Farm Market:</strong> Discover fresh apples, pumpkins, and autumnal treats.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Picnicking: </strong>Grab a basket, some local treats, and head to one of the state’s scenic parks.
<ul>
<li><strong>Sandy Point State Park:</strong> Offering stunning views of the Chesapeake Bay Bridge, it’s a great spot for a fall picnic.</li>
<li><strong>Centennial Park:</strong> Located in Ellicott City, the lake and surrounding foliage create a perfect picnic setting.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Orienteering:</strong> This combination of map reading and running is a thrilling way to explore the outdoors.
<ul>
<li><strong>Patuxent River Park:</strong> Known for its orienteering events, where participants navigate to specific points using a map and compass.</li>
<li><strong>Fair Hill Natural Resource Management Area: </strong>Hosts orienteering events suitable for both beginners and experts.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Off-road Driving:</strong> Explore the rugged terrains of Maryland.
<ul>
<li><strong>Assateague Island National Seashore:</strong> Get an off-road vehicle permit and explore the beaches, spotting wild horses along the way.</li>
<li><strong>Green Ridge State Forest:</strong> Offers off-road driving for those looking for a challenging and scenic drive.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Night Sky Gazing: </strong>The fall season offers clear skies, perfect for stargazing.
<ul>
<li><strong>Garrett County:</strong> Being one of the darkest spots in Maryland, it’s perfect for observing constellations.</li>
<li><strong>Harriet Tubman Underground Railroad State Park:</strong> Occasionally hosts night sky programs with telescopes available for public use.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Caving:</strong> Explore the underground wonders of Maryland.
<ul>
<li><strong>Crystal Grottoes Caverns: </strong>Maryland’s only public show cave, located in Boonsboro, offers guided tours of its stunning formations.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Maryland’s fall landscape offers a plethora of outdoor activities, from the thrill of mountain biking to the serenity of bird-watching. The cooler temperatures and mesmerizing hues make it an ideal time to explore the state’s natural beauty. Whether you’re a seasoned adventurer or just looking for a relaxing day outdoors, Maryland in the fall has something to offer everyone.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>USA</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/usa/maryland-outdoors-fall/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/usa/maryland-fall-colors.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Karnataka, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/010-karnataka/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/india/mountain-kudremukh.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Nandan Upadhya on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Karnataka, located in the southwestern region of India, is a treasure trove of natural beauty, historical landmarks, and vibrant culture. From its pristine beaches to its lush Western Ghats, the state offers a plethora of outdoor activities for nature lovers, adventure enthusiasts, and history buffs. Here’s a detailed guide to some of the best outdoorsy things to do in Karnataka:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Trekking in the Western Ghats:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Kudremukh Trek:</strong> Located in the Chikkamagaluru district, Kudremukh is a popular trekking destination known for its picturesque landscapes and rich biodiversity.</li>
<li><strong>Kumara Parvatha Trek:</strong> This is one of the most challenging treks in Karnataka, offering stunning views of the Pushpagiri Wildlife Sanctuary.</li>
<li><strong>Tadiandamol Peak:</strong> The highest peak in Coorg, Tadiandamol offers a moderate trek with panoramic views of the surrounding hills and valleys.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Beach Hopping:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gokarna:</strong> Famous for its serene beaches like Om Beach and Kudle Beach, Gokarna is a haven for beach lovers and backpackers.</li>
<li><strong>Karwar:</strong> Located near the Goa-Karnataka border, Karwar boasts of pristine beaches and a tranquil ambiance.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Waterfall Visits:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Jog Falls:</strong> One of the highest plunge waterfalls in India, Jog Falls is a majestic sight, especially during the monsoon season.</li>
<li><strong>Abbey Falls:</strong> Located in Coorg, this waterfall is surrounded by coffee plantations and spice estates.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Wildlife Safaris:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bandipur National Park:</strong> Home to tigers, elephants, and various species of deer, Bandipur offers jeep safaris for wildlife enthusiasts.</li>
<li><strong>Nagarhole National Park:</strong> Another gem in Karnataka, Nagarhole is known for its rich flora and fauna, including the majestic Bengal tiger.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>River Rafting in Dandeli:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Dandeli, located in the Uttara Kannada district, is a hotspot for white-water rafting. The Kali River offers thrilling rapids for both beginners and experienced rafters.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explore the Ruins of Hampi:</strong>
<ul>
<li>A UNESCO World Heritage Site, Hampi is an ancient village known for its ruins that date back to the Vijayanagara Empire. While it’s a historical site, the boulder-strewn landscapes offer a unique outdoor experience.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Camping in Sakleshpur:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Nestled in the Western Ghats, Sakleshpur is a perfect destination for camping amidst coffee plantations and misty hills.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Caving in Badami:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Badami is renowned for its rock-cut cave temples. However, the region also offers adventurous caving experiences amidst its red sandstone cliffs.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Paragliding in Nandi Hills:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Located near Bangalore, Nandi Hills is a popular spot for paragliding, offering breathtaking views of the surrounding landscapes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Cycling in Coorg:</strong>
<ul>
<li>The winding roads of Coorg, surrounded by lush greenery and coffee estates, make it an ideal destination for cycling enthusiasts.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong> Karnataka is a diverse state that offers a mix of natural beauty, adventure, and history. Whether you’re looking to relax on a beach, trek through dense forests, or explore ancient ruins, Karnataka has something for every outdoor enthusiast. So, pack your bags and set out to explore the myriad wonders of this beautiful state!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/010-karnataka/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/india/mountain-kudremukh.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Jharkhand, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/009-jharkhand/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/waterfalls-ranchi.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Tapan Kumar Choudhury on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Jharkhand, often referred to as the “Land of Forests,” is a state in eastern India that boasts a rich tapestry of natural beauty, tribal culture, and ancient history. From dense forests and waterfalls to wildlife sanctuaries and ancient temples, Jharkhand offers a plethora of outdoor activities for nature lovers and adventure enthusiasts. Here’s a detailed guide to some of the best outdoorsy things to do in Jharkhand:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Visit the Dassam Falls:</strong> Located near Ranchi, the Dassam Falls is a picturesque waterfall that cascades from a height of 144 feet. The serene environment and the thundering sound of the water make it a popular spot for picnics and relaxation.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore the Betla National Park:</strong> One of the first national parks in India to become a tiger reserve, Betla National Park is home to a variety of wildlife, including tigers, elephants, and deer. The park also features ancient forts and watchtowers, offering a blend of nature and history.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trek to Parasnath Hill:</strong> Considered one of the most sacred Jain pilgrimage sites, Parasnath Hill is the highest peak in Jharkhand. Trekkers can explore the lush greenery, enjoy panoramic views, and visit the numerous Jain temples scattered across the hill.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Discover the Rock Gardens and Kanke Dam:</strong> Located in Ranchi, the Rock Gardens are an artificial garden with sculptures and waterfalls, offering a peaceful retreat. Adjacent to it is the Kanke Dam, a perfect spot for boating and enjoying sunset views.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Experience the Beauty of Hundru Falls:</strong> One of the most famous waterfalls in Jharkhand, Hundru Falls plunges from a height of 320 feet, creating a spectacular sight. The area around the falls is ideal for picnics and photography.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit the Tribal Villages:</strong> Jharkhand is home to various tribal communities, each with its unique culture and traditions. Visitors can take guided tours to tribal villages, interact with the locals, and learn about their way of life.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Go Caving in the Sita Kund Hot Springs:</strong> Located in Munger, the Sita Kund is a natural hot spring believed to have medicinal properties. Nearby, there are ancient caves that adventurers can explore, offering a mix of nature and mythology.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Relax at the Dimna Lake:</strong> Situated near Jamshedpur, Dimna Lake is an artificial reservoir surrounded by hills and forests. It’s a popular spot for boating, picnicking, and enjoying the tranquility of nature.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore the Deoghar Temples:</strong> Deoghar, also known as Baidyanath Dham, is a significant pilgrimage site for Hindus. The ancient temples, surrounded by hills and forests, offer a spiritual experience amidst nature.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wildlife Safari in Hazaribagh National Park:</strong> This park is a haven for wildlife enthusiasts, with its dense forests and diverse fauna, including tigers, leopards, and various species of deer. The park also offers jeep safaris for a closer encounter with the wild.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Jharkhand is a treasure trove of natural beauty and cultural richness. Whether you’re an adventurer, a nature lover, or someone seeking spiritual solace, Jharkhand has something to offer for everyone. So, pack your bags and get ready to explore the mesmerizing landscapes and vibrant culture of this beautiful state.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/009-jharkhand/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/waterfalls-ranchi.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Himachal Pradesh, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/008-himachal-pradesh/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/tents-dharamshala.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Himachal Pradesh, often referred to as the “Land of Gods,” is a paradise for nature lovers and adventure enthusiasts. Nestled in the western Himalayas, this Indian state offers a plethora of outdoor activities that cater to people of all ages and interests. From trekking in the rugged mountains to paragliding over scenic valleys, Himachal Pradesh promises an unforgettable experience. Here’s a detailed guide to the outdoorsy things you can indulge in while visiting this mesmerizing state:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Trekking</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Triund Trek</strong> : A relatively easy trek that offers panoramic views of the Dhauladhar range. The trek starts from McLeod Ganj and is perfect for beginners.</li>
<li><strong>Hampta Pass Trek</strong> : This moderate trek connects the Kullu Valley to the Lahaul and Spiti valleys and offers diverse landscapes, from green pastures to barren lands.</li>
<li><strong>Pin Parvati Pass Trek</strong> : A challenging trek for seasoned trekkers, it offers a mix of dense forests, meadows, and glacial valleys.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Paragliding in Bir Billing</strong>
<ul>
<li>Recognized as the second-highest paragliding site in the world, Bir Billing offers an exhilarating experience as you soar over the picturesque landscapes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>River Rafting in Kullu</strong>
<ul>
<li>The Beas River offers thrilling white-water rafting experiences. Navigate through the rapids and enjoy the adrenaline rush.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Camping</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Solang Valley</strong> : Known for its lush greenery and snow-capped peaks, it’s an ideal location for camping under the stars.</li>
<li><strong>Tosh</strong> : A hidden gem, Tosh offers serene landscapes and is perfect for those looking to escape the crowds.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mountain Biking in Manali</strong>
<ul>
<li>Explore the rugged terrains of Manali on a mountain bike. The trails offer varying levels of difficulty, catering to both beginners and experts.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Ice Skating in Shimla</strong>
<ul>
<li>During the winter months, Shimla’s ice-skating rink comes alive. It’s one of the oldest natural ice-skating rinks in South Asia.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Rock Climbing in Palampur</strong>
<ul>
<li>Test your physical strength and mental endurance by climbing the rocky terrains of Palampur.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Fishing in Tirthan Valley</strong>
<ul>
<li>The pristine waters of the Tirthan River are home to the famous trout fish. Spend a day fishing and enjoy the tranquility of the surroundings.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Visit the Great Himalayan National Park</strong>
<ul>
<li>A UNESCO World Heritage Site, this park is home to diverse flora and fauna. Go on a safari or a guided nature walk to explore its beauty.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Hot Springs in Manikaran</strong>
<ul>
<li>After a tiring day of adventure, relax and rejuvenate in the natural hot springs of Manikaran. The waters are believed to have therapeutic properties.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>Himachal Pradesh is not just about picturesque landscapes and serene valleys; it’s an adventurer’s playground. Whether you’re an adrenaline junkie or someone looking to connect with nature, Himachal has something for everyone. So, pack your bags and set out on an adventure of a lifetime in this Himalayan paradise.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/008-himachal-pradesh/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/tents-dharamshala.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Haryana, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/008-haryana/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/aravali-hills.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" data-description="An ariel view of Aravalli Hills, Haryana"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Pushpinder Pal Singh on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Haryana, a North Indian state, is often overshadowed by its more touristy neighbors like Rajasthan and Himachal Pradesh. However, Haryana has its own unique charm and offers a plethora of outdoor activities for those who love to explore. From ancient archaeological sites to lush green landscapes, Haryana is a haven for outdoor enthusiasts. Here’s a detailed guide on the outdoorsy things to do in Haryana:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Sultanpur National Park</strong> : Located near Gurgaon, this bird sanctuary is a paradise for bird watchers. The park is home to over 250 species of birds, both migratory and resident. The best time to visit is during the winter months when you can spot migratory birds like the Siberian crane, flamingos, and pelicans.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Damdama Lake</strong> : Situated in Sohna, Gurgaon, Damdama Lake is one of the biggest natural lakes in Haryana. It’s a popular spot for boating, rock climbing, and hot air ballooning. The serene environment makes it perfect for picnics and day outings.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Aravalli Biodiversity Park</strong> : Spread over 692 acres, this park in Gurgaon is a testament to the conservation efforts in Haryana. It’s a great place for nature walks, jogging, and spotting various plant species.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Morni Hills</strong> : The only hill station in Haryana, Morni Hills is located in the Panchkula district. It’s an ideal destination for trekking, bird watching, and enjoying panoramic views of the Shivalik range.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bhondsi Nature Camp</strong> : Located near Gurgaon, this camp offers adventure activities like rock climbing, rappelling, and obstacle courses. It’s a great place for team-building exercises and family outings.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Archaeological Sites in Rakhigarhi</strong> : Dive into history by visiting Rakhigarhi, one of the largest Indus Valley Civilization sites. Explore the ancient ruins and get a glimpse of life from thousands of years ago.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Yadavindra Gardens (Pinjore Gardens)</strong> : Located in Pinjore, these Mughal-style gardens are a treat for the eyes. The terraced gardens, fountains, and historical structures make it a must-visit.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Badkhal Lake</strong> : Once a popular bird-watching spot, this lake near Faridabad is now a favorite for boating and picnics. The surrounding Aravalli hills add to its beauty.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Heritage Transport Museum</strong> : Though not entirely outdoors, this museum in Taoru offers a unique experience. Explore the evolution of transportation in India, from palanquins and bullock carts to vintage cars and trains.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Kurukshetra</strong> : Dive deep into Indian mythology by visiting Kurukshetra, the land of the Bhagavad Gita. The Brahma Sarovar and Krishna Museum are must-visits. You can also attend the light and sound show that depicts the Mahabharata war.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>Haryana, with its rich history, diverse flora and fauna, and picturesque landscapes, offers a myriad of outdoor activities for every kind of traveler. Whether you’re a history buff, a nature lover, or an adventure enthusiast, Haryana has something for everyone. So, pack your bags and set out to explore this hidden gem of North India!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/008-haryana/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/aravali-hills.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Andhra Pradesh, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/001-andhra-pradesh/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/grand-canyon-of-india.jpg" class="prview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Chaitanya Chunduri on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Andhra Pradesh, one of India’s southeastern coastal states, is often overshadowed by its more popular neighbors. However, it houses an array of pristine landscapes, historical landmarks, and diverse ecosystems, making it an ideal destination for outdoor enthusiasts. From serene beaches to enchanting hill stations and vibrant wildlife, Andhra Pradesh has something for everyone.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Explore the Beaches of Visakhapatnam</strong> : Often referred to as ‘Vizag’, Visakhapatnam boasts some of the most pristine beaches in India. Ramakrishna Beach and Rushikonda Beach are popular spots for sunbathing, water sports, and soaking in the coastal vibes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trek in the Eastern Ghats</strong> : The Eastern Ghats mountain range runs through Andhra Pradesh and offers various trekking trails. One of the most famous is the Araku Valley, known for its lush landscapes, waterfalls, and tribal culture.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Boat Rides on the Godavari</strong> : The Godavari, India’s second-longest river, flows through Andhra Pradesh. A boat ride on this river, especially through the scenic Papikondalu range, offers mesmerizing views of the ghats and the serene waters.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit the Belum Caves</strong> : These are the second-largest natural caves in the Indian subcontinent. The underground caverns, with their long passages, spacious chambers, and freshwater galleries, offer a unique spelunking experience.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bird Watching at Pulicat Lake</strong> : Pulicat Lake, on the border of Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu, is the second-largest brackish water lake in India. It’s a haven for birdwatchers, especially during the winter months when it sees an influx of migratory birds like flamingos.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Waterfalls Galore</strong> : Andhra Pradesh has several stunning waterfalls. Among the must-visit are the Talakona, Ethipothala, and Katiki waterfalls. These natural wonders are perfect for a day trip and offer great photo opportunities.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sri Venkateswara National Park</strong> : Located near the holy city of Tirupati, this park is home to a variety of flora and fauna. It’s an excellent place for wildlife enthusiasts looking to spot endangered species like the Indian Giant Squirrel and the Golden Gecko.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore the Mangroves of Coringa Wildlife Sanctuary</strong> : Situated near the town of Kakinada, this sanctuary boasts one of India’s largest mangrove forests. It’s home to several species of birds and animals, including the fishing cat and otters.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cycling in Horsley Hills</strong> : A serene hill station located near Madanapalle, Horsley Hills is an ideal spot for cycling. The cool climate, gentle slopes, and panoramic views make for an enjoyable ride.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit the Kondapalli Reserve Forest</strong> : Located near Vijayawada, this forest reserve is known for its rich biodiversity and the Kondapalli Fort. It’s a great place for a day trek and exploring the region’s history.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sailing at Krishna River</strong> : The Krishna River offers sailing experiences, especially around Vijayawada. You can also indulge in other water sports like jet-skiing and parasailing.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore the Ruins of Gandikota (cover image of this article)</strong> : Often referred to as the “Grand Canyon of India,” Gandikota is a small village on the banks of the Pennar River. It’s famous for its spectacular gorge, ancient fort, and the mesmerizing views it offers.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>Andhra Pradesh is a treasure trove of outdoor experiences waiting to be explored. Whether you’re a nature lover, adventure seeker, or just someone looking to escape the hustle and bustle of city life, this state has something to offer. So pack your bags and embark on an outdoor journey through the enchanting landscapes of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/001-andhra-pradesh/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/grand-canyon-of-india.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Chhattisgarh, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/005-chhattisgarh/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/tamdaghumar-waterfall.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Vishal mallik on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Chhattisgarh, located in the central-eastern part of India, is often touted as the “Rice Bowl of India.” But beyond its agricultural significance, the state is a treasure trove of natural beauty, ancient history, and cultural splendor. If you’re an outdoor enthusiast, Chhattisgarh has an array of activities that can quench your thirst for adventure and scenic beauty. Let’s dive into some of the most exhilarating outdoorsy things you can indulge in when visiting this fascinating state.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Chitrakote Waterfalls</strong> : Often referred to as the ‘Niagara Falls of India’, the Chitrakote Waterfalls are the broadest waterfalls in the country. Located on the Indravati River, it’s a sight to behold, especially during the monsoon season when the waters are in full spate.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Kanger Valley National Park</strong> : A paradise for nature lovers, this national park houses the famous Kutumsar caves and Kailash caves. You can explore these subterranean wonders, witness unique stalactite and stalagmite formations, and even spot diverse wildlife species in the park.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tirathgarh Waterfalls</strong> : Cascading from a height of about 300 feet, the Tirathgarh Waterfalls is another scenic marvel of Chhattisgarh. The falls split into multiple cascades, creating a surreal and picturesque environment.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Indravati National Park</strong> : Home to the endangered wild buffalo, this national park offers a rich bio-diversity. Safaris are organized for tourists to witness the diverse fauna including tigers, leopards, and numerous bird species.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trekking at Mainpat</strong> : Known as the ‘Shimla of Chhattisgarh’, Mainpat is a plateau covered with lush greenery. It offers several trekking trails that wind through dense forests, waterfalls, and offer breathtaking views of the valleys.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Barnawapara Wildlife Sanctuary</strong> : Spread over an area of around 245 sq km, this sanctuary is a haven for wildlife enthusiasts. You can spot animals like leopards, porcupines, pythons, and various species of deer.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sirpur Archaeological Site</strong> : While it’s primarily a historical site, the open-air ruins and lush green surroundings make it an exciting outdoor experience. Explore ancient temples, monasteries, and structures dating back to the 5th-8th centuries AD.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rafting on River Indravati</strong> : For those seeking adrenaline, white-water rafting in the turbulent waters of River Indravati offers a thrilling experience. The river’s rapids provide a challenging adventure for enthusiasts.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Camping</strong> : There are numerous spots in Chhattisgarh that offer camping opportunities. From the forests of Barnawapara to the plains of Mainpat, you can camp under the stars and experience the serenity of nature.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biking</strong> : The topographical diversity of Chhattisgarh offers ample opportunities for mountain biking. Trails through dense forests, meandering rivers, and rocky terrains challenge both novice and seasoned bikers.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit Ghatarani Waterfalls</strong> : Located near Raipur, Ghatarani is a popular picnic spot. The dense forests surrounding the falls, the serene ambiance, and the temple dedicated to Goddess Durga nearby, make it a must-visit.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>Chhattisgarh, with its rich tapestry of forests, waterfalls, wildlife, and ancient ruins, offers an array of outdoor activities that cater to every kind of traveler. Whether you’re a history buff, nature lover, or an adventure junkie, this state promises unforgettable experiences amidst its pristine landscapes. So, pack your bags and get ready to dive into the untouched beauty of Chhattisgarh.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/005-chhattisgarh/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/tamdaghumar-waterfall.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Arunachal Pradesh, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/002-arunachal-pradesh/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/sela-pass.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Mayur More on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Arunachal Pradesh, situated in the northeastern corner of India, is a mesmerizing state adorned with lush landscapes, snow-capped mountains, and intricate cultural tapestry. Dubbed the “Land of the Rising Sun,” this region offers an array of outdoor activities for both the adventurous spirit and the nature lover. Here’s a curated list of outdoorsy things to do in Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Tawang Monastery Visit:</strong> Tawang Monastery, founded in the 17th century, is the largest monastery in India and second largest in the world. Perched at an elevation of about 3,000 meters, it offers panoramic views of the valley below. The monastery complex houses a library, a museum, and a massive gilded statue of Lord Buddha.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sela Pass Drive (cover image of this post):</strong> Sela Pass, at 13,700 feet, is one of India’s high-altitude mountain passes. Driving through this scenic route covered in snow for most of the year is an unparalleled experience. The nearby Sela Lake, a serene and pristine water body, is another must-visit spot.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>River Rafting in Siang:</strong> For the adrenaline junkies, the Siang River offers exciting opportunities for white-water rafting. The river’s challenging rapids amidst the scenic landscapes make for a thrilling experience.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trekking in the Himalayas:</strong> Arunachal Pradesh offers a myriad of trekking trails ranging from easy to challenging. Popular treks include the Mechuka Valley Trek, Bailey Trail Trek, and Gorichen Peak Trek. These trails pass through verdant forests, alpine meadows, and offer views of majestic Himalayan peaks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pakhui Wildlife Sanctuary Exploration:</strong> This sanctuary is a haven for wildlife enthusiasts. Home to tigers, elephants, hornbills, and a variety of other species, it offers the opportunity for jungle safaris and bird watching.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit Ziro Valley:</strong> Recognized as a World Heritage Site, Ziro Valley is a visual treat with its green paddy fields and traditional Apatani villages. The Ziro Music Festival, held annually, attracts music lovers from across the globe.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bumla Pass:</strong> Close to the Indo-China border, Bumla Pass is a place of significant historical importance. At an elevation of 15,200 feet, the journey to Bumla offers some of the most spectacular views of the Eastern Himalayas.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore the Parshuram Kund:</strong> Located on the Brahmaputra plateau, Parshuram Kund is a significant Hindu pilgrimage site. Every year during Makar Sankranti, thousands of pilgrims visit the kund to take a holy dip, believed to wash away their sins.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Jaswant Garh War Memorial:</strong> Located 21 km from Tawang, this war memorial is dedicated to the brave soldiers who sacrificed their lives during the 1962 Indo-China war. The place provides a deep sense of patriotism amidst the natural beauty of the region.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit Namdapha National Park:</strong> Namdapha, the third-largest national park in India, is a biodiversity hotspot. From the snow leopard and red panda to myriad bird species, this park is a testament to Arunachal’s rich natural heritage.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Angling in Pasighat:</strong> The Siang River near Pasighat is perfect for angling and fishing activities. Golden Mahseer is the prize catch here.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Explore Tribal Villages:</strong> Arunachal Pradesh is home to 26 major tribes and over 100 sub-tribes. Visiting tribal villages, witnessing their unique customs, dances, and way of life can be a transformative experience.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion:</strong></p>
<p>Arunachal Pradesh, with its untouched beauty and diverse topography, is a paradise for outdoor enthusiasts. Whether it’s the thrill of white-water rafting, the tranquility of a Himalayan trek, or the allure of deep-rooted tribal cultures, Arunachal promises an unforgettable experience.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/002-arunachal-pradesh/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/sela-pass.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Gujarat, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/007-gujarat/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/camel-rann-of-kutch.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Faisal Khatri on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Gujarat, located on the western coast of India, is known for its rich history, architectural wonders, and vibrant culture. However, it also offers a plethora of outdoor activities and natural wonders that are often overlooked. From pristine beaches to wildlife sanctuaries, and from desert landscapes to serene lakes, Gujarat has it all. Here’s a guide to outdoorsy things you can indulge in when visiting this magnificent state:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>The White Rann of Kutch (cover image of this post)</strong> : The Rann of Kutch is a salt marsh in the Thar Desert. Its ethereal beauty peaks during the full moon nights. The Rann Utsav, a cultural festival, is a great time to visit and experience the local music, dance, and crafts, amidst this lunar-like landscape.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gir National Park</strong> : The last bastion of the Asiatic lion, this park is a haven for wildlife enthusiasts. Apart from the lions, one can also spot leopards, antelopes, and a variety of bird species. Opt for a safari tour for a thrilling adventure.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Marine National Park, Narara Island</strong> : Situated near Jamnagar, it’s India’s first marine sanctuary. With a low tide, one can walk around the park and spot octopuses, pufferfish, crabs, and even dolphins in the distant waters.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trekking in Saputara</strong> : Saputara is Gujarat’s only hill station. It offers various trekking and hiking trails amidst the Sahyadri range. The Governor’s Hill is a popular trek, offering panoramic views of the entire hill station and the adjoining valleys.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Beaches of Gujarat</strong> : Mandvi, Dwarka, and Diu are among the most popular beaches. The Mandvi beach is known for its serenity and camel rides, while Dwarka, apart from its religious significance, offers mesmerizing sunset views.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Paragliding in Saputara</strong> : For those seeking an adrenaline rush, paragliding over the Sahyadri range offers an exhilarating experience. Get a bird’s eye view of the lush greenery, lakes, and undulating landscapes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Camping at Blackbuck National Park</strong> : Located in Velavadar, this park is home to a large population of the Indian Blackbuck. Camping under the stars and waking up to the sight of these elegant creatures is an experience to cherish.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Boating in Nal Sarovar Bird Sanctuary</strong> : A paradise for bird watchers, Nal Sarovar houses more than 200 species of birds. Rent a boat at dawn to witness the spectacular view of migratory birds taking flight.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Dinosaur Fossil Park at Raiyoli</strong> : Believe it or not, Gujarat also has a connection with the prehistoric era. Raiyoli near Balasinor is known to be the third-largest dinosaur fossil site in the world and also houses a fossilized dinosaur egg hatchery.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wild Ass Sanctuary</strong> : Situated in the Little Rann of Kutch, this sanctuary is home to the endangered Indian Wild Ass. Other inhabitants include flamingoes, pelicans, and cranes. Opt for a jeep safari for the best experience.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Thol Lake Bird Sanctuary</strong> : Just a short drive from Ahmedabad, Thol Lake is another bird watcher’s paradise, especially during the winter months when it welcomes various migratory species.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cycling Tours</strong> : Several agencies offer cycling tours across Gujarat. Popular routes cover coastal areas, heritage sites, and the countryside, allowing tourists to experience Gujarat from a unique perspective.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Khijadiya Bird Sanctuary</strong> : Located near Jamnagar, this sanctuary boasts of a mix of freshwater lakes, salt pans, and marshy lands, providing diverse habitats for different bird species.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>Visiting Gujarat provides an opportunity to delve deep into its natural beauty, making it an enriching experience for every kind of traveler. Whether you’re an adventure seeker, wildlife enthusiast, or just someone looking for serenity amidst nature, Gujarat promises an unforgettable outdoor escapade.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/007-gujarat/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/camel-rann-of-kutch.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Goa, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/006-goa/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/goa-beach-surfers.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Miguel Baixauli on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Goa, a small state on the southwestern coast of India, is widely known for its beautiful beaches, vibrant nightlife, and rich culture. While many travelers are drawn to its beach parties and laid-back vibe, the region also offers a plethora of outdoor activities for those seeking adventure and a closer communion with nature. Here’s a detailed list of outdoorsy things to do in this tropical paradise:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Beach Hopping</strong> : Goa has a vast coastline with over 50 beaches, each having its unique charm. Start with the bustling Baga and Calangute beaches, and gradually explore the quieter ones like Kakolem and Galgibaga.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Water Sports</strong> : Indulge in activities like jet-skiing, parasailing, banana boat rides, and windsurfing. Palolem and Anjuna beaches are hotspots for such activities.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Scuba Diving and Snorkeling</strong> : The waters surrounding Goa are brimming with marine life. Grande Island and Pigeon Island are perfect spots to explore the underwater world.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trek to Dudhsagar Waterfalls</strong> : Located on the Goa-Karnataka border, this four-tiered waterfall is one of the tallest in India. Trekkers can revel in the surrounding greenery and also enjoy a dip in the water.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Spice Plantation Tours</strong> : Witness the cultivation of spices like cardamom, vanilla, and nutmeg. The Sahakari Spice Farm and the Tropical Spice Plantation offer guided tours where you can learn about traditional Goan farming.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wildlife Sanctuaries</strong> : Visit the Bhagwan Mahavir Wildlife Sanctuary or the Mollem National Park. These protected areas are home to diverse fauna like leopards, gaurs, and the Malabar giant squirrel.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bird Watching</strong> : The Dr.&nbsp;Salim Ali Bird Sanctuary, located on the island of Chorão, is a haven for ornithologists and bird lovers. The mangrove habitat is home to species like kingfishers, eagles, and herons.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>White Water Rafting</strong> : For adrenaline junkies, the Mhadei River offers thrilling white water rafting experiences, especially during the monsoon season.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Kayaking</strong> : Navigate the serene backwaters of Goa on a kayak, a perfect activity for early mornings or late afternoons.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Hot Air Balloon Ride</strong> : Float over the Goan landscape and catch a bird’s eye view of its picturesque beaches, forests, and towns.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cycling Tours</strong> : Rent a cycle and traverse through Goa’s charming villages, past paddy fields, and along the coastline. This is an eco-friendly way to explore the region’s nooks and corners.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Rock Climbing</strong> : The rugged terrains of Goa provide ample opportunities for rock climbing. Sada in Chorla Ghat is a popular spot.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Beach Camping</strong> : Away from the bustling resorts, indulge in beach camping, especially in South Goa. Palolem and Galgibaga beaches are known for such camping experiences.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fishing Trips</strong> : Engage with the locals and learn traditional fishing techniques. Many operators offer deep-sea fishing expeditions too.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Windsurfing</strong> : With the Arabian Sea on one side and consistent winds, Goa offers optimal conditions for windsurfing. Beginners can head to the Dona Paula bay for lessons.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Paragliding</strong> : Feel the rush as you glide over Goa’s coastal belt, enjoying panoramic views of its beaches and sea.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>To truly experience Goa’s outdoorsy side, one must step beyond the beach shacks and immerse in its diverse terrains and activities. Whether you’re an adventure seeker or a nature lover, Goa has something to offer for everyone. Remember to respect the environment and local customs as you explore this beautiful land. Safe travels!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/006-goa/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://f005.backblazeb2.com/file/outdoorsy-indians/things-to-do/goa-beach-surfers.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Assam, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/003-assam/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/one-horn-rhino.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Santanu Misra on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Assam, a beautiful state nestled in the northeastern part of India, is an adventurer’s and nature lover’s paradise. Renowned for its rich biodiversity, majestic Brahmaputra River, lush tea gardens, and diverse culture, Assam offers numerous outdoor activities that captivate the soul. If you’re planning to immerse yourself in Assam’s natural splendor, here’s a list of outdoorsy things to do:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Kaziranga National Park</strong> : One of India’s premier wildlife refuges, this UNESCO World Heritage site is home to the world’s largest population of the one-horned rhinoceros (cover image of this post). Go on a jeep or elephant safari to spot rhinos, elephants, tigers, wild buffalos, and various species of birds.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Manas National Park</strong> : Another UNESCO World Heritage site, this park is a biodiversity hotspot. It boasts of tigers, elephants, and the endangered golden langur. The serene Manas River flowing through the park adds to its beauty.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>River Rafting in Brahmaputra</strong> : Experience the thrill of white-water rafting in one of the world’s major rivers. The rafting expedition will give you an adrenaline rush as you navigate through challenging rapids amidst breathtaking landscapes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Majuli Island</strong> : Claimed to be the world’s largest river island, Majuli is situated in the Brahmaputra River. A cycle or bike tour of the island is a great way to explore its natural beauty, tribal villages, and the traditional Assamese mask-making art.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tea Garden Tours</strong> : Assam is synonymous with tea, and a visit to its vast tea gardens is a must. Walk amid the green tea bushes, learn about the tea-making process, and relish fresh tea right from the gardens.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sualkuchi Village</strong> : Often referred to as the ‘Manchester of Assam’, this village is renowned for its silk weaving. Paddle down the Brahmaputra to reach this village and witness the intricate art of weaving Assam’s famous Muga and Eri silk.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trekking</strong> : Assam’s hills and terrains offer exciting trekking opportunities. Popular trails include those in the North Cachar Hills and Karbi Anglong.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bird Watching at Dibru Saikhowa National Park</strong> : A haven for bird lovers, this national park is home to migratory birds like the Siberian crane, Greater Adjutant Stork, and many more. Enjoy a boat ride and spot birds in their natural habitat.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Camping</strong> : For those who love to be close to nature, Assam offers many camping spots, especially near the Brahmaputra’s sandy banks. Listen to the sounds of nature, enjoy campfires, and gaze at the starry sky.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visiting the Wetlands</strong> : Assam’s wetlands, such as Deepor Beel and Son Beel, are rich in flora and fauna. These places are perfect for boat rides, fishing, and observing nature’s beauty.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Exploring Historical Sites</strong> : While not strictly an “outdoorsy” activity, visiting historical sites such as the ancient temples of Sivasagar or the Ahom-era monuments can be an open-air experience offering insights into Assam’s rich history.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cruise on the Brahmaputra</strong> : Take a luxury cruise on the Brahmaputra River, which offers a blend of nature exploration, cultural experiences, and serene relaxation.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>In conclusion, Assam’s diverse landscapes and cultural richness make it an ideal destination for outdoor enthusiasts. Whether you are an adventure seeker, a nature lover, or someone looking to immerse in the local culture, Assam offers something for everyone. So, pack your bags and get ready to explore the untouched beauty of this northeastern gem of India.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/003-assam/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/one-horn-rhino.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Outdoorsy Things to Do in Bihar, India</title>
  <link>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/004-bihar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/ghora-katora-lake.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Photo by Arto Suraj on Unsplash</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Bihar, located in the eastern part of India, is a state filled with a rich cultural heritage and historical significance. While it might be renowned for its ancient temples, historic sites, and unique traditions, Bihar also offers a variety of outdoor activities for those looking to experience its natural beauty and get adventurous. Here’s a detailed guide to the outdoorsy things you can do in Bihar:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Explore the Nalanda University Ruins</strong>: The ancient Nalanda University, a UNESCO World Heritage Site, was once a global center for learning. Though the ruins are more historical than outdoorsy, the vast expanse of the complex offers plenty of walking and exploration opportunities.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit the Valmiki National Park</strong>: Situated in the West Champaran district, Valmiki National Park is Bihar’s only national park and tiger reserve. Besides the Bengal tiger, the park is home to various other wildlife species like leopards, Indian bison, and several species of deer. Here, you can indulge in a jungle safari, bird watching, or simply trek through the natural landscapes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Boating in Kakolat Waterfall</strong>: Kakolat Waterfall is one of the state’s prime tourist attractions, especially during the monsoon. Located near Nawada district, the waterfall and the pond at its base are surrounded by greenery, offering a serene atmosphere. Boating is a popular activity here.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Cycle around Bodhgaya</strong>: Bodhgaya is a UNESCO World Heritage site known for the Mahabodhi Temple, where Gautama Buddha is said to have attained enlightenment. Renting a cycle to explore the town and its surrounding areas provides a unique perspective on its history, architecture, and local life.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trek to Mundeshwari Hills</strong>: The Mundeshwari Devi Temple, believed to be the oldest Hindu temple in India, sits atop the Mundeshwari Hills. Trekking up the hill not only offers a spiritual experience but also mesmerizing views of the surrounding landscape.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sailing on the Ganges in Patna</strong>: The Ganges, one of the most revered rivers in India, flows through Patna, Bihar’s capital. You can rent a boat or join organized tours that offer sunset and sunrise sails. The experience of floating on this historic river, especially during sunrise or sunset, is ethereal.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pilgrimage walks</strong>: Bihar has been significant in the life of Lord Buddha. Pilgrimage walks or ‘Parikramas’ around important Buddhist sites such as Rajgir, Nalanda, and Bodhgaya can be both spiritual and a way to enjoy the outdoors.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Visit the Kanwar Lake Bird Sanctuary</strong>: This is one of Asia’s largest freshwater oxbow lakes and a haven for bird watchers. The sanctuary hosts numerous migratory birds during winter months. It’s a paradise for photographers and nature lovers.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Picnic at Manjhar Kund</strong>: Also known as Manjhar K waterfall, it is one of the most beautiful waterfalls in Bihar, located near Sasaram. It’s a great spot for a picnic and to enjoy the natural surroundings.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Climbing the Griddhakuta Hill</strong>: Located in Rajgir, this is another significant site related to Buddhism. A climb up the hill is both an exercise and a pilgrimage, and the views from the top are rewarding.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Bihar, with its rich history intertwined with natural beauty, offers a plethora of options for outdoor enthusiasts. Whether you’re seeking adventure, serenity, or spiritual fulfillment, Bihar has something to offer. Remember to respect local customs and the environment, ensuring that these treasures are preserved for future generations.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Are we Missing Something?
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Help us build the ultimate outdoor bucket list! If there’s a destination you swear by that didn’t make our list, please enlighten our community in the comments.</p>
</div>
</div>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>India</category>
  <guid>https://outdoorsyindians.com/things-to-do/india/004-bihar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://storage.googleapis.com/outdoorsy-indians-images/things-to-do/ghora-katora-lake.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
